<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a treatise out of ecclesiastical history translated from an ancient Greek manuscript in the publick library at Oxford by Humfrey Hody ... and published under the title of The unreasonableness of a separation from the new bishops, to shew that although a bishop was unjustly deprived, neither he nor the church ever made a separation, if the successor was not an heretick : to which is added, the canons in the Baroccian manuscript omitted by Mr. Hody.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2980</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18575</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12258200</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12258200</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57618</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28220)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57618)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 167:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a treatise out of ecclesiastical history translated from an ancient Greek manuscript in the publick library at Oxford by Humfrey Hody ... and published under the title of The unreasonableness of a separation from the new bishops, to shew that although a bishop was unjustly deprived, neither he nor the church ever made a separation, if the successor was not an heretick : to which is added, the canons in the Baroccian manuscript omitted by Mr. Hody.</title>
                  <author>Bisbie, Nathaniel, 1635-1695.</author>
                  <author>Browne, Thomas, 1654?-1741.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by J. Wells ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Variously attributed to N. Bisbie and T. Browne. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops.</term>
               <term>Unreasonableness of a separation from the new bishops.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57618:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57618:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO A TREATISE OUT OF <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory,</hi> Tranſlated from An Ancient <hi>Greek</hi> MANUSCRIPT in the Publick Library at <hi>Oxford,</hi> BY <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MFRET HODY,</hi> B. D. &amp;c. And Publiſhed under the Title of <hi>The Unreaſonableneſs of a Separation from the</hi> New BISHOPS, TO SHEW, <hi>That although a Biſhop was unjuſtly deprived, neither he nor the Church ever made a Separation, if the Succeſſor was not an Heretick.</hi> To which is added, The CANONS in the <hi>Baroccian</hi> Manuſcript Omitted by Mr. <hi>HODY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>J. Wells,</hi> near S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1691.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57618:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:57618:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THat a <hi>Separation</hi> is always <hi>unreaſonable</hi> on one ſide or the other, is without all queſtion; but that it is unreaſonable to ſeparate from <hi>New Biſhops</hi> that are placed in the Sees of Biſhops, who are uncanonically depoſed, for this Cauſe only, that they are in Poſſeſſion, upon what Reaſon and Juſtice ſoever, of the ſaid Epiſcopal Sees, is very ſtrange Doctrine, and ſuch as was never, I think, heard of in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> till this Treatiſe was publiſhed. For in the Senſe of the Catholick Church in her Canons and Conſtitutions, the New Biſhop himſelf in ſuch a Caſe makes the Separation, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Communion with the true Biſhop is not to ſeparate from the wrongful Poſſeſſor; but to keep our former Place and Station, to adhere to the Right, and not to follow thoſe, who have ſet themſelves up in oppoſition to it.</p>
            <p>But the Doctrin, which this Anonymous Greek Author is brought to vouch for to the World, is of ſuch a perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Nature, and, if it be allowed, muſt have ſuch deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Conſequences in the Church, that I cannot but think, that all Men, who have a ſincere Love for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whatever their Opinions may be in other Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, will not be ill pleaſed to ſee it proved, that there is no Example to be found of this in the Practice of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, till it was reduced to ſo low and deplorable a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb facs="tcp:57618:3"/> as to be no longer a Pattern for Imitation, but a Caution rather for us to beware of thoſe things which brought the <hi>Greeks</hi> into that Diſtreſs, under which they have ſo long groaned.</p>
            <p>And if we will but give our ſelves the leaſt leiſure to conſider; what is then that can bring more certain and ſpeedy Ruine upon a Church, than to act by ſuch a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as makes all Eccleſiaſtical Authority have its ſole and entire dependance upon external Force and Power, and upon the caſual Succeſs and Events of things?</p>
            <p>For if, when the Civil Magiſtrate ſhall diſplace a Biſhop for any frivolous cauſe, or for no Cauſe at all, but with the greateſt and moſt apparent Injuſtice, all Chriſtians ſhall be obliged in Conſcience to ſubmit to the Intruder, if he be but Orthodox, and not to adhere to their lawful Biſhop; this utterly deſtroys all Church Authority, and gives it up wholly into the Power of the Magiſtrate, who may ſet up what Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop he pleaſes, provided they be no Hereticks, and change them as often as he pleaſes, and the Clergy and People ſhall be bound in Conſcience to take no further notice of the diſpoſſeſſed, but to live under the new ones, be they never ſo many, and never ſo bad, in all Acts of Communion and Obedience. Now unleſs the Church can be ruined by nothing but Hereſie, or there be nothing that can render a Biſhop unqualified for his Station but Hereſie, it is evident that this Doctrine leaves it at the Mercy of the Prince, whether there ſhall long be any Church in his Dominions.</p>
            <p>It is manifeſt, that theſe Principles make all Church Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ineffectual, and expoſe the Church to all the Miſchiefs of <hi>Eraſtianiſm:</hi> For if a Prince ſhould prefer an excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated Perſon to the See of the Biſhop, by whom he ſtands excommunicated; ſuppoſing only that he was not excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated for Hereſie; this Perſon, tho never ſo juſtly excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, muſt be owned and obeyed inſtead of the Biſhop who excommunicated him; which lodges all Church Power
<pb facs="tcp:57618:3"/> in the Prince, and makes all Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures of no effect for the Benefit and Preſervation of the Church, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>A Schiſmatical Prince, by this Doctrine, may ſet up Schiſmatical Biſhops, and the Church will have no Remedy againſt them. For inſtance, if <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had been a Novation or Donatiſt, he might have depoſed the Rightful Biſhops, and have ſet up Novations or Donatiſts in their ſtead; if thoſe Sects were then only Schiſms; and they were no more at firſt: But whoever can imagin, that the Clergy and People of that Age would have communicated with them, and have deſerted their true Biſhop, may indeed believe all that our Author has ſaid. Tho the truth is, according to his Principles, no Prince can be a Schiſmatick, becauſe he may make what Biſhops he pleaſes, and ſo can make what Church he pleaſes, and it will be the Duty of Chriſtians to communicate, not with their Biſhops, but with their Prince, or, which is the ſame thing, with what Biſhops he appoints.</p>
            <p>A Popiſh Prince might ſet up Popiſh Biſhops amongst us; for he could never want Men, who at leaſt upon as good Grounds and from as good Authorities, as thoſe upon which this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is propounded to us, would prove that Popery is no Hereſie.</p>
            <p>A Prince of a Latitudinarian Faith may by theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples give us Socinian Biſhops: For the Diſciples of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copius</hi> and <hi>Curcellaeus</hi> will undertake to prove that the Points in Controverſie are not of neceſſity to Salvation, and do not conſequently involve the Aſſertors of them in Hereſie.</p>
            <p>And if a Prince ſhould deſign never ſo well, for the Glory of God, and the Intereſt of Religion; yet how eaſie it is for Princes to be miſtaken and miſled in things of this nature, we may ſee in <hi>Conſtantine</hi> himſelf, who was deceived by the <hi>Arians</hi> into a good Opinion of them, after the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> even to the ſending St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> away from his See; tho he took care to keep it void from him till his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,
<pb facs="tcp:57618:4"/> to prevent a Schiſm, which by the Practice of the Church, could not otherwiſe have been avoided. But this is moſt of all remarkable in the unhappy Reign of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> who cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly was a very Devout Prince, and had very good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in calling ſo many Synods, and therefore the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers often mention him, with Reſpect and with great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion; but was miſerably deluded and impoſed upon by the <hi>Arians,</hi> and perſuaded to baniſh all the Orthodox Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and fill up the Sees with thoſe of their own number. But we muſt obſerve, that tho <hi>Conſtantius</hi> believed, that the <hi>Arians</hi> were not Hereticks but Orthodox, and died in his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, as S. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> declares, tho S. <hi>Gregory Nanianzen</hi> and <hi>Theodor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> ſay the contrary: and therefore cannot be ſuppoſed to want any inclinations to Depoſe <hi>Athanaſius</hi> by his own Power, and the <hi>Arians</hi> wanted no Malice againſt <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> nor no Authority with the Emperour to put him upon it, yet becauſe, according to the Doctrine profeſſed on both ſides, this could not be done, they were forced to be at all that trouble to get a Synod of their own Party to effect it. But if it be left to the Arbitrary Will of the Prince to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Orthodox Biſhops at his Pleaſure, and ſupply the vacancies with any whom he thinks fit, and their Dioceſes muſt be obliged in Conſcience to acknowledge them, he will be ſure in a ſhort time to have ſuch Biſhops as ſhall deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine that only to be Hereſie, which he will have to be ſo; and it is a vain thing to ſay, that Heretical Biſhops muſt not be promoted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or that they muſt not be obeyed, for in a little time by this Doctrine there will be nothing reputed Hereſie, nor Schiſm, but to hold a different Opinion, and a different Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manion from that of the Prince.</p>
            <p>But to come nearer home, this Doctrine denies the Church a Power, which is granted to be in all other Societies; own no Head but of their own chooſing, or who is, otherwiſe, regularly ſet over them according to their Charter or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; and it ſeems, if King <hi>James</hi> had put in new Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb facs="tcp:57618:4"/> againſt the conſent of the Chapters, the Dioceſes would have been obliged to obey them, though the Fellows of <hi>Magdalen</hi> College in <hi>Oxford</hi> were bound in Conſcience not to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a Preſident, who was forced upon them againſt their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</p>
            <p>It may perhaps be ſaid that we are ſecured from all the inconveniences that would follow from this Doctrine, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as by the Laws of the Land no Biſhop can be forced upon us by the King; but he muſt be choſen by the Chapter of the Cathedral Church of the Dioceſe, to which he is nominated. But firſt, if this Doctrine be calculated only for our own Church, and we muſt be governed by a different Rule from the reſt of the Catholick Church, why then is the Practice of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church brought to recommend it to us. But if this have been the Doctrine and Practice of all Churches, we are not to imagine, that the Laws of the Land can make it no ſin, but a Duty to ſeparate from intruding Biſhops, when the Laws of God and of his Church enjoyn the contrary. For the Laws of our Country muſt ceaſe to oblige us in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience when they are inconſiſtent with the Doctrine and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Church in all Ages; and if theſe have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the Principles, and this the Practice of the Church, as it is now pretended, to own the preſent Biſhop, whoever he be, if he be no Heretick; I doubt it will be in vain to alledg the Laws of the Land againſt an Intruder, when he is once in Poſſeſſion, as long as he can keep his Poſſeſſion; but we muſt have Biſhops <hi>de Facto,</hi> and muſt be bound in Conſcience to ſubmit to them, by whatever ill means they came in at firſt. But ſuppoſe that the Laws of the Land would be a ſecurity to us, (as they have hitherto been, and will be ſtill, if we retain our old Principles) yet how can we be ſure that the Laity will be more tender of the Honour and welfare of the Church than the Clergy themſelves are? And that, if the Clergy give up the Eccleſiaſtical Authority, they will not be willing to conſent to it; and be contented that a Prince ſhould be abſolute in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical
<pb facs="tcp:57618:5"/> Affairs, if he will but act according to Law, in Civil?</p>
            <p>But whatever ſecurity there may be from the Secular Power to the Church, ſince it is incorporated into the State; yet by theſe Principles the Church could not have ſupported it ſelf againſt the Attempts of Schiſmaticks before the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours became Chriſtians; and if the Civil Government ſhould withdraw its Protection, it is plain this Scheme leaves the Church no Power to defend it ſelf againſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation of one Biſhop upon another: for by this Model of Church-Government, if a Biſhop get into Poſſeſſion of anothers Dioceſe by any way whatſoever, whether by the Secular Power, or by any other means, provided he be no Heretick<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he is from thence forth to be looked upon as the true Biſhop, notwithſtanding any Canon of the Church againſt his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pation. So that this Notion does effectually diſſolve all Church-Government, and leaves no Power and Authority in the Church to preſerve it ſelf, but leaves it at the Mercy not only of the Civil Magiſtrate, but of any Invader, who is no Heretick or does not appear to be ſuch. <hi>Novatian,</hi> if he could have got into Poſſeſſion of the Epiſcopal Throne, muſt by theſe Principles have been ſubmitted to as Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> than which nothing can be more abſurd, or more contrary to the Doctrine and Practice of the Church in all Ages. And if the Cauſe of the New Biſhops can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by none, but ſuch Principles, it is plain, that it is not to be defended at all: for we muſt not contradict the Doctrine of the Church in all Ages, to ſerve a preſent Turn; nor maintain the Church in this Age ſo as to have no Church left for the next.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall not here undertake further to ſhew how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and deſtructive theſe Principles are to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to Religion in general, much leſs is it my buſineſs to ſtate the Caſe now in Controverſie. I intend only to purſue the Author of this Treatiſe through his Diſcoveries,
<pb facs="tcp:57618:5"/> which he pretends to make in Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory: and if I can ſhew that this <hi>Greek</hi> has put a fallacy upon us, I hope we ſhall not ſuffer our ſelves to be cheated by the impertinent and falſe Stories of an obſcure Writer of no Name nor Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but who appears to have lived in the moſt decayed and worſt State of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, when their Sermons were nothing but ill digeſted Rapſodies, which, both for their Stile and Senſe, will ſcarce endure the Reading; their Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Hiſtories nothing but Legends of Miracles, and all their Hiſtories, both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, full of ſuch idle Stories as moſt Men are aſhamed to tell after them; and when by their Vices and Ignorance they had rendred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ripe for that Deſtruction, which ſoon after came upon them. It is to thoſe Ages that we owe the loſs of ſo many of the Works of the Fathers of the Firſt Centuries, and the Corruption of others, to Countenance the Tenets and Practices of their own times; and it is no wonder, that when their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were ſo often Depoſed at the pleaſure of the Emperour upon frivolous or rather upon very unjuſt pretences, ſome ſhould endeavour to make it believed, that ſuch Proceedings muſt be acquieſced in, according to the Practice of former Ages in the like caſes; when the decay of all ſound Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and true Religion, and of all good Orders and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline both in Church and State was ſo great, and their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions ſo incurable, which were principally occaſioned, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely heightened by the frequent changes of the Patriarchs, that they at laſt brought utter ruin upon the Empire, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the Church to the Arbitrary Pleaſure of the <hi>Grand Seignior.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is worth our obſervation, that notwithſtanding it had been ſo cuſtomary for the Emperors in the <hi>Greek</hi> Church to Depoſe their Biſhops, yet after the Thirteenth Century, (and how long after we cannot tell) it was matter of diſpute in that Church, whether they ought to Communicate with the new Biſhops; ſo that this Author's whole Book is a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb facs="tcp:57618:6"/> to his very deſign in writing it: for if they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly for ſo many Ages ſubmitted to the Intruding Biſhops as often as they were put up, how came there at that time to be any doubt about it? Or how could it then be neceſſary to prove, with ſo much Pains and Formality, that which he would make us believe had been the conſtant Practice of their Church in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Age? If what he ſays had been true, it could have needed no Proof to them, and ſince he was forced to be at ſo much Pains to prove it to the <hi>Greeks</hi> themſelves, that this had ever been the Practice of their own Church, it is a good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to us that it was not the Practice of it; for if it had been all along practiſed, no Man almoſt among them could have been ignorant of it, ſince, according to his own account, there was ſcarce any Age but afforded too many Inſtances of the Removal of Biſhops.</p>
            <p>Conſidering all this, I wonder that the learned Writer of the Preface ſhould tell us, that this Author is ſo unexception<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a Judg to appeal to: for I ſhould be very ſorry, if any exception ſhould lye againſt the Authors of our own time, that does not lye againſt this. Yes ſays he, <hi>Surely no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Aſperſions of time-ſerving, courting Preferment, or the like, that might be caſt upon any that ſhould write now in this Cauſe, can take place againſt this Author, ſo remote from the preſent Age and Controverſie.</hi> I hope uncharitable Aſperſions will take place neither againſt this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor nor any other, but it is too much to perſuade us that Clergy men were never ſwayed by Intereſt till now of late; this would be too great a Satyr upon the preſent Age, and would betray too great ignorance of all that are paſt; for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more notorious than that mankind have had the ſame Paſſions and Frailties in all Times; and if we were to ſearch for Examples of Prejudice, and Deceit, and Perſidiouſneſs, and all manner of ill Practices, we ſhould no where ſooner find them, than in thoſe degenerate Ages of the Church. And he tells us, that <hi>our Author probably was one of the Biſhops</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:57618:6"/> 
               <hi>that aſſiſted at the new Patriarchs Conſecration,</hi> for whoſe ſake all this was written: ſo that the Caſe was the ſame, and the Controverſie the ſame, and the difference is only in Time, and Place, and perhaps in ſome other as inconſiderable Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall apply my ſelf to the <hi>Greek</hi> Author, and in Anſwer to him ſhall conſider all that is ſaid in the Preface to ſtrengthen and ſupport his Authorities from Antiquity.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57618:7"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57618:7"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVER TO A TREATISE OUT OF Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Shall follow our Author in his own way, tho he does not always proceed according to order of Time; which is no Argument of his Skill or Exactneſs, but ſhews that he took up his Materials as he found them, and placed them without any great Care or Method. And to ſhew his Judgment, we ſhall ſee he has ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times brought Inſtances which are nothing to his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>He begins with S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 1.</note> in the firſt place would inſinuate that he was Uncanonically Ordained, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received the Order of Deacon by the hands of <hi>Meletius,</hi> who was placed by the <hi>Arians</hi> in the Sea of <hi>Euſtathius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sebaſtia</hi> in <hi>Armenia,</hi> and was afterwards Tranſlated to <hi>Antioch,</hi> whilſt <hi>Euſtathius</hi> was yet living: and he obſerves, that <hi>Meletius,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, was removed to <hi>Antioch</hi> by the joynt conſent of both the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox and <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops, and that both S. <hi>Baſil</hi> and S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> were Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Deacons by him.</p>
            <p>By all this we are given to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that <hi>Euſtathius</hi> of <hi>Sebaſtia</hi> had great wrong done him, and that <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letius</hi> being beſides made Biſhop by the <hi>Arians</hi> could never become a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Biſhop.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt point: <hi>Euſtathius</hi> was condemned in two Synods for his ill Tenets and Practices. He was firſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socrat. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 43.</note> Depoſed by his own Father <hi>Eulalius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Cappodocia,</hi> and was afterwards condemned in a Synod at <hi>Gangre</hi> in <hi>Paphlagonia,</hi> becauſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was Depoſed, he had done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things contrary to the Canons. <q rend="inline">He had forbidden to Marry, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to abſtain from Meats; he had cauſed ſeveral Men and their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57618:8"/> Wives to depart from each other; thoſe who would not come to Church, he had perſuaded to Communicate in their Houſes. He made ſeveral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants leave their Maſters upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Piety. He were the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of a Philoſopher (which was the miſdemeanor his Father at firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him for) and had introduced a new kind of diſtinct Habit for all of his own Sect. He cauſed Women to be Shorn. He declared againſt the ſet Faſts of the Church, and appointed his Followers to Faſt on <hi>Sundays.</hi> He would not ſo much as admit any Prayers to be made in the Houſes of married Perſons, and commanded all to avoid, as a thing abominable, the Benediction and Communion of a Prieſt, who had a Wife, tho he had married her before he entred into Orders, and he both did and taught many other things of like nature.</q> 
               <hi>Sozomen</hi> relates, that beſides his being <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sozom. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> Depoſed at <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Cappodocia,</hi> and at <hi>Gangre,</hi> he was Excommunicated by a Synod at <hi>Neoceſaria</hi> in <hi>Pontus,</hi> and Depoſed by <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> for his Treachery in ſome buſineſs that he had been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with, and was Convicted of Perjury in a Synod of <hi>Antioch.</hi> To all this I need not add, that he was an <hi>Arian,</hi> and renounced the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, which he had once profeſſed, and that S. <hi>Baſil</hi> often complains of his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baſil. Ep.</hi> 72, 73, 74. 78, 79. 196.</note> falſe and perverſe dealing, and beſides ſays, that it was reported of him, that he had reordained ſome of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelites, tho he could ſcarce believe it, ſince no Heretick was ever known to dare to do it. Theſe certainly are Crimes which would juſtifie his being Depoſed, and it could be no fault in <hi>Meletius</hi> to preſide in the See of a Biſhop, who for ſo juſt Reaſons was condemned in ſeveral Synods, and had had <hi>Anathema</hi> pronounced againſt his Doctrines.</p>
            <p>The Second thing <hi>viz.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Mele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> was Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted by the <hi>Arians,</hi> was ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed a great objection againſt him, and had like to have been of very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſequence to the Church of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h.</hi> For tho <hi>Meletius</hi> had ſhewn himſelf a zealous and learned Aſſertor of that Orthodox Faith, and was high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed by the Orthodox Biſhops, who were mightily ſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sfied with his Promotion to the See of <hi>Antioch:</hi> yet there was a Party of Men who ſtill retained a Prejudice againſt him upon the account of his Conſecration; and during his Baniſhment under <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Lucifer Calaritanus</hi> coming to <hi>Antioch</hi> Conſecrated <hi>Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inus</hi> Biſhop of that City, which, when he ſaw the Orthodox Biſhops, and particularly <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> of <hi>Vercelles,</hi> diſapprove of it, gave the firſt occaſion to <hi>Lucifer</hi> to begin that Sect, which from him took its denomination. <hi>Meletius</hi> at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from Exile, under <hi>Julian,</hi> finds <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Sozom. l</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> divided into three Parties; one, that followed <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roius</hi> the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhop; another that Communicated with <hi>Paulinus;</hi> and a third, that adhered ſtill to himſelf, as their lawful Biſhop: the <hi>Arians</hi> had poſſeſſed themſelves of all the Churches within the City, but one of the ſmall Churches, which they allowed <hi>Pauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> ſo that he was forced to hold his Aſſemblies without the Gates. <hi>Mele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſuffered a ſecond Baniſhment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Valens;</hi> and when he was reſtored by <hi>Gratian, Paulinus</hi> being then An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr. l.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> thoſe who were of <hi>Meletius</hi>'s Communion, endeavoured to have the difference ſo Compoſed, that both he and <hi>Paulinus</hi> might together Preſide in that See. But <hi>Paulinus</hi> refuſed to agree to it, alledging that <hi>Meletius</hi> had received his Ordination from <hi>Arian</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. Upon this the People were in a Ferment, and cauſed <hi>Meletius</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Throne in one of the Churches without the City. This bred great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57618:8"/> between the Parties, but at laſt they came to this agreement; That whoſoever of theſe two Biſhops ſhould die firſt, the ſurvivour ſhould be the ſole Biſhop of the See; and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſix Men then in <hi>Antioch,</hi> who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Death of them, might probably make pretenſions to the Succeſſion, they were all ſworn to this Agreement. And thus the difference was Compoſed, only the <hi>Luciferians</hi> would by no means be prevailed with to Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with him, but ſet up ſeparate Congregations. Thus it was according to the account <hi>Socrates</hi> gives of this Matter; but as <hi>Theodorite</hi> relates it, <hi>Sapores,</hi> whom the Emperor had ſent to inſpect and regulate this Buſineſs, ſeeing the great equity and condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Meletius,</hi> put him into Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> of the Biſhoprick: for he makes no mention of any Agreement between him and <hi>Paulinus,</hi> but only ſays, that <hi>Meletius</hi> had the See delivered up to him, and <hi>Paulinuus</hi> remained Biſhop only of that Party, which adhered to him.</p>
            <p>This being the caſe, ſince <hi>Meletius</hi> was ſo eminent a defender of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Faith, as he is confeſſed by all to have been, and had twice ſuffered Baniſhment for it, and during his firſt Baniſhment had one irregularly placed in his See, and did afterwards, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo great a Provocation, uſe all the Condeſcenſion that could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in ſuch a Caſe; it could be no juſt Prejudice againſt him, that he was at firſt made Biſhop by the <hi>Arians,</hi> or rather by the <hi>Semi-Arians,</hi> or <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> who upon occaſion would ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scer. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, and pretended to have no exceptions to the Doctrines contained in it, but were for taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as not being found in Scripture, as if the difference had been only in Terms, contriving in the mean time all the ways poſſible to undermine the Faith by their own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. But it does not appear that <hi>Meletius</hi> ever was an <hi>Arian</hi> himſelf; on the contrary the Orthodox Fathers never mention him, but with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt commendations; and he ſeems to have been impoſed upon by the <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> and <hi>Semi-Arians</hi> for a while, who diſguiſed and diſſembled their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. For when he was called to give an account of his Faith in the preſence of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> himſelf, in the Synod <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 31.</note> at <hi>Antioch,</hi> he declared himſelf to the entire ſatisfaction of the Orthodox Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; and it was no more than they expected from him, and were before well aſſured of, which made them ſo deſirous to have him advanced to the See of <hi>Antioch.</hi> And tho <hi>Socrates</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 44.</note> ſays, that <hi>Meletius</hi> ſubſcribed the Form of Faith which <hi>Acacius</hi> produced in the Synod of <hi>Selencia;</hi> yet this ſeems to be a miſtake, which perhaps the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, which he plainly enough diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers for <hi>Paulinus,</hi> might betray him to; for <hi>Meletius</hi>'s name is not to be found among the Subſcriptions to the Creed of <hi>Acacius</hi> ſet down in <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiphan. Haer.</hi> 73.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now it was determined in this Caſe, in a Council at <hi>Alexandria</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Athanaſ. Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. ad Ruhnianum inter ejus op. Tom. 2. p. 40. &amp; apud Conc. Nicen. 2. Act. 1. Col. 75.</note> that the worſt of Hereticks, the very Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal and Leading Men among them upon the renouncing their Errors, and reconciling themſelves to the Church by Repentance, ſhould be received to Communion, tho not to Officiate as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57618:9"/> Clergymen; but the leſs culpable, who had been abuſed and miſled, were likewiſe to be permitted the Exerciſe and Adminiſtration of their Function. Which is no more than was practiſed in the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> it ſelf towards the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops, who renounced their Hereſie, and ſigned the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, as S. <hi>Hierom</hi> urges in his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue <hi>Adverſus Luciferianos,</hi> where he diſputes this point at large. This was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc. Nic. Can.</hi> 8. <hi>Socr. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Valeſ. de Schiſm. Donatiſt.</hi>
               </note> all along the Practice of the Church towards the <hi>Arians</hi> and <hi>Novations,</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Meletians,</hi> who were ſo denominated from <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letius</hi> the <hi>African</hi> Biſhop, to admit of their Orders, upon their Reconciling themſelves to the Church, and thus it was confirmed and eſtabliſhed in the Council of <hi>Nice.</hi> And to the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of this Council of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria, Lucifer Calaritanus</hi> himſelf had <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Sozom. l.</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13.</note> given his aſſent by his Deacon, whom he had ſent thither for that purpoſe, and <note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Aſſenſus eſt huic ſententiae Occidens, &amp; per tam neceſſarium concilium Satanae faucibus mundus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reptus eſt.</hi> Hieron. adv. Luciferian.</note> all the Weſtern Church ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of this Decree as the only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie. For the true Reaſon why the Weſtern Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops eſpouſed the Cauſe of <hi>Paulinus</hi> againſt <hi>Meletius</hi> was not for any Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection they had againſt his Ordination (which was made an Objection by none but the <hi>Luciferians)</hi> but becauſe he had been repreſented in the Weſt as an Heretick, as S. <hi>Baſil</hi> complains, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baſil. Ep.</hi> 321. 349.</note> as it appears from S. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s two Epiſtles to <hi>Damaſus,</hi> wherein he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to know of him, with whom he ſhould Communicate at <hi>Antioch:</hi> and <hi>Paulinus</hi> was thought little better of in the Eaſt, for receiving to Communion the Aſſociates of <hi>Marcellus.</hi> But <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d. Epiſt.</hi> 74. <hi>&amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphan. Haer.</hi> 77.</note> was received as Patriarch of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> in the General Council of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> and dying there, S. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> in the preſence of that Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Aſſembly celebrated his memory with the higheſt Praiſes in his Funeral Oration. And upon his death <hi>Flavia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> was by unanimous conſent choſen <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. C. P. apud Theod. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Socr. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 15.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and the choice confirmed in that General Council, tho <hi>Paulinus</hi> was yet living, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon nominated <hi>Euagrius</hi> for his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, but he dying ſoon after <hi>Pauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> no other Biſhop was choſen in his room.</p>
            <p>But the ſtate of this Controverſie, as it lay between the <hi>Meletians</hi> and <hi>Luciferians,</hi> is a direct confutation of the whole deſign of this Authors Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. For if all Chriſtians are obliged to look no further than to the Biſhop in Poſſeſſion; <hi>Paulinus</hi> was put into poſſeſſion of the See of <hi>Antioch,</hi> whilſt <hi>Meletius</hi> was in Baniſhment, and he at his return was forced to hold his Aſſemblies without the City; yet the <hi>Meletians</hi> never thought this any Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for their compliance, nor did the Adherents of <hi>Paulinus</hi> ever urge it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them: they urged that <hi>Meletius</hi> had been made Biſhop by <hi>Arians,</hi> and that Plea was over-ruled by the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of a Council held at <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria;</hi> whereas if our Authors notion had then been good Doctrine, it muſt ſoon have decided the Queſtion: for no Man could deny but <hi>Paulinus</hi> was actual Biſhop in the abſence of <hi>Mele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> which was a better pretence than if he had been turned out to make way for him; and ſo it is impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſible, but this Argument muſt have been inſiſted upon, if this had been then an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Doctrine; and it had been at leaſt a good Argument in the Eaſtern Church, where our Author would make us believe, it was always the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom to Communicate with the Biſhop for the time being, however he came to be ſo: and it is incredible, that in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57618:9"/> ſo weighty a Controverſie, which was ſo long depending, no Man ſhould once think of the thing, which could alone decide it, when it was ſo obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to all capacites, and is ſuppoſed to have been received into the conſtant Practice of the Church in all ſuch caſes. St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> himſelf after the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> death of <hi>Meletius,</hi> for three whole years would not Communicate with ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, and at laſt, as all, but <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> teſtifie, was ordained Presbyter by <hi>Flavianus,</hi> that is, he eſpouſed the cauſe of the <hi>Meletians,</hi> and took di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly the contrary ſide to that, which he ought to have taken by theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. For it was a received Maxim, that regularly there could be but one Biſhop of one Church at the ſame time (for if a Biſhop appointed his own Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, and took him in his life time for an Aſſiſtant to him, this was an extraordinary caſe, and he retained the Authority ſtill to himſelf, or it was at his own choice, whether he would part with any of it) and if the Biſhop in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion were to be the <hi>one Biſhop, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letius</hi> had been precluded by <hi>Paulinus,</hi> when he re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urned from Baniſhment, and <hi>Paulinus</hi> was afterwards left in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion upon the death of <hi>Meletius.</hi> 'Tis plain then that this Doctrine was unknown to the whole Church at that time, and particularly to S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> upon whoſe account this is brought, and whoſe Caſe comes now to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
            <p>The Author obſerves that upon the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 2.</note> Depoſing of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom, Arſacius</hi> was placed in his See, who in fourteen months time muſt be ſuppoſed to O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons; or if he did not, yet <hi>Atticus</hi> ſucceeded him, whilſt S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> was yet alive and in Exile. <hi>Atticus</hi> ſat as Patriarch twenty years, and yet all his Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were never queſtioned, but were received by the Church, as if they had been Canonical. <hi>Atticus</hi> was ſucceeded by <hi>Siſinnius,</hi> and he by <hi>Neſtorius;</hi> and both <hi>Atticus</hi> and <hi>Siſinnius</hi> were owned as Patriarchs by <hi>Celeſtine</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtorius;</hi> and in the General Council of <hi>Epheſus</hi> no exceptions were made to the Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Patriarchs of <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> only <hi>Neſtorius</hi> himſelf was De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for Hereſie. To enforce all this yet further, the Writer of the Preface cites ſome paſſages out of the life of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> written by <hi>Palladius,</hi> to ſhew what the Opinion of that Father was in his own Caſe, and how far he was from inſiſting upon any Right he had to be acknowledged ſtill, as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch, when he was once Depoſed: For, ſays he, <hi>S. Chryſoſtom adviſed and charged the Biſhops his Friends more than once, That as they loved Chriſt, none of them ſhould leave his Church upon his account: That they muſt keep Communion with his Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and not rend and divide the Church. And he enjoyned ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Women that attended there, that as they hoped to obtain Mercy from God, they ſhould pay the ſame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Good will to his Succeſſor by a fair Election, that they had done to himſelf: for the Church could not be without a Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this notwithſtanding, upon exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we ſhall find that S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> was clearly of another mind, than he is here repreſented to be of, and that there is nothing in his Caſe, which will in the leaſt favour this Authors Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. I have already obſerved, how much contrary S <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> acted to theſe Principles in the caſe of <hi>Meleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and I ſhall now make it appear, that he was evidently againſt them in his own.</p>
            <p>The account <hi>Palladius</hi> gives us is <note place="margin">Pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this: S. <hi>Chryſoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> before his firſt Baniſhment, when he perceived what violent Methods his Adverſaries would take; ſpoke to the forty Biſhops, who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57618:10"/> were met with him: That as they loved Chriſt none of them would leave his Church upon his account: <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I am n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w ready to be offered, and the time of my departure is at hand, in S.</hi> Paul<hi>'s words. I ſhall undergo many Sufferings, I ſee, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part this life.</hi> And afterwards; <hi>To me to live is Chriſt, and to die is gain,</hi> and, <hi>am I better than the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. p.</hi> 68.</note> 
               <hi>than the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that I ſhould be immortal?</hi> From whence it is plain that he was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry apprehenſive that his Enemies had a deſign upon his life, and that they would not ſuffer him to live much longer: <note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Pallad p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. 68.</note> 
               <hi>For it was commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that he was to be beheaded.</hi> At this one of them expreſſed, how much they were troubled for the Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and Confuſion that would befal the Church, when wicked Men ſhould Uſurp the Government of it. Upon which he again exhorts them not to forſake their Churches: <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Preaching did not begin with me, nor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib. p.</hi> 69.</note> 
               <hi>will it end with me: did not</hi> Moſes <hi>die? And was not</hi> Joſhua <hi>appointed to ſucceed him? Did not</hi> Samuel <hi>die? And was not</hi> David <hi>anointed?</hi> Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah <hi>departed this life, but did he not leave</hi> Baruch <hi>behind?</hi> Elijah <hi>was taken up into Heaven, but then did not</hi> Eliſha <hi>Prophecy? S.</hi> Paul <hi>was beheaded, but did he not leave</hi> Timothy, Titus, Apollos, <hi>and innumerable others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him?</hi> When he had ſaid this, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulyſius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Apamea</hi> in <hi>Bithy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> puts him in mind, that if they retained their Churches they muſt be forced to Communicate, and to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the Depoſing him: to which S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> anſwers, that he would have them hold Communion to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a Schiſm in the Church, but by no means to Subſcribe; for he was conſcious to himſelf of nothing for which he ought to be Depoſed, or thruſt out of his See. Juſt before his ſecond Baniſhment, he ſpeaks to <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias</hi> the Deaconeſs with ſome others, ſaying, <hi>I ſee the things concerning me have an end, I have finiſhed my Courſe, and probably you will never ſee my face more: this one thing I deſire of you, that none of you omit your accuſtomed Good-will and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance upon the Church; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall be Ordained without his own ſeeking, and</hi> 
               <note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Ibid. p 90.</note> 
               <hi>againſt his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, by a general conſent, that you would obey him, as you would do me: for the Church cannot be without a Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is evident both from the Words themſelves, and from the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in which he ſpoke them, that S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> both times looked upon himſelf as a dying Man, when he uſed theſe words in taking his leave of the Biſhops, and of the Deaconeſſes, and therefore they cannot import, that he would have them ſubmit to a Biſhop, who ſhould ſucceed him during his life.</p>
            <p>But if we allow the words their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Latitude, and take them in the greateſt extent that they will poſſibly admit of, they can amount to no more than this, not that they ſhould ſubmit to <hi>any</hi> Biſhop, who ſhould ſucceed him, whilſt he was living; but to one, who ſhould not be deſirous or fond of it, but ſhould come in againſt his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, and by an unanimous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; by which we can underſtand no leſs, than that he means one, who was not of the Party againſt him, nor had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57618:10"/> any hand in thruſting him out; and if ſuch an one were choſen unanimouſly, who was a friend to his Cauſe, and lamented the great injuſtice done him, and who unwillingly and upon neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty only could be prevailed upon to fill the See, and who therefore muſt have been as willing to have given way to him, as the true Patriarch, if ever he ſhould have returned; if ſuch an one were choſen; (and ſuch an one he muſt he, if he were choſen by general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: for never any Biſhops departure was more grievous to all but the Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Depoſed him, than S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi>'s was) then, according to this Senſe of his words, he adviſes them not to divide the Church upon his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but to joyn in Communion with ſuch a Biſhop, ſince this was the only means to preſerve the Churches Peace. Which is a conditional Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or a Declaration that he would forgoe his own Right upon condition that ſuch a Biſhop were choſen as he there mentions. But, if we ſuppoſe this to be S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s meaning, the See was diſpoſed of to men, who were very far from being ſuch Biſhops as he exhorted them to ſubmit to. For all his Friends endured great hardſhips under <hi>Arſacius,</hi> and <hi>Atticus</hi> had been <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pallad. p.</hi> 95. <hi>Soz. lib.</hi> 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 27. <hi>Phot. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bli. Cod.</hi> 277.</note> the chief Incendiary againſt him. And this is the excuſe which <hi>Photius</hi> makes for ſome Expreſſions, that ſeemed to him a little too ſevere, which S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> uſed concerning <hi>Arſacius</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Cyriacus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to be convinced that S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> did not deſign that they ſhould ſubmit to <hi>any</hi> Biſhop, that ſhould be ſet up, we need only conſider that theſe very Perſons, to whom he gave this in charge, never would ſubmit either to <hi>Arſacius</hi> or <hi>Atticus,</hi> at leaſt during his Life; but ſuffered all that they could do to them, rather than they would comply, and S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> wrote many Epiſtles to theſe very Biſhops and Deaconeſſes, to comfort and ſupport them under the ſevere afflictions, which they endured upon this account: And when <hi>Palladius</hi> himſelf, and ſo many other Biſhops, with the reſt of the Clergy ſuffered ſo much in S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi>'s Cauſe, as is mentioned in his Life, it is paſt all belief, that neither any of the reſt, nor <hi>Palladius,</hi> who is ſuppoſed to be the Author of this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Life, and was one of thoſe Biſhops to whom S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> gave theſe directions, ſhould call to mind what he had ſaid to them; but the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops as well as Deaconeſſes ſhould with one conſent act contrary to what S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in his laſt words required of them, and ſhould either miſtake him, or forget what he had ſaid, or ſhould chooſe to ſuffer any thing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than obſerve his advice, and do what he had told them was their Duty. But as his Friends could not have ſo little reſpect for him, or ſo little care of themſelves, as to forget ſo ſoon, what it would have been ſo much for their own eaſe and ſafety to remember: ſo he would not have failed in ſome one of his Epiſtles at leaſt to put them in mind of it, and would never have let them ſuffer ſo much, contrary to that Duty, which his laſt words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated to them, taking no care af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to remind them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what God and the Church required of them. If he had never heard of their condition, or had never had an opportunity to write to them about it, it is ſcarce poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible they ſhould miſunderſtand him ſo, as to run themſelves into ſuch need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and indeed ſinful ſufferings; but when he held a Correſpondence with them in his Baniſhment, and wrote ſo often upon this very Subject, it is incredible that they ſhould ſuffer for not doing that, which he had exhorted them to do, and that he among all his Conſolations ſhould forget that which would alone have given them effectual
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57618:11"/> and preſent relief, and ſhould omit to tell them, that they ſuffered when they needed not, and in a Cauſe, in which they could not ſuffer with a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>But this is not all: S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt. Epiſt.</hi> 26. 27.</note> does not only omit to tell them, that they needed not, and ought not to ſuffer, but applauds them for ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſo good a Cauſe, and exhorts them to perſeverance, and applies thoſe Scriptures to them, which pronounce bleſſings upon thoſe, who ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake: He tells them they ought not to value their lives in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 36. 46. 71. 90.</note> ſuch a Cauſe, being certain of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Heaven. He <note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c Ep. 83. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Ep. 85.</note> extols the Apoſtolical Courage and Conſtancy of the Biſhops and Clergy, who were in Priſon, and compares them to S. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> both in their Sufferings and in the juſtneſs of their Cauſe; and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it, as a more glorious thing to ſuffer ſo much, and ſo long for the Vindication of the Primitive Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Diſcipline, than it was for him to be beheaded for telling <hi>Herod,</hi> that it was not lawful for him to have his Brother <hi>Philip</hi>'s Wife: S. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſuffered but once; but he bids them ſay, <hi>we are ready to ſuffer ten thouſand Deaths rather than comply with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. He exhorts the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 99.</note> Biſhop and Clergy of <hi>Scythopolis</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, as to their own Honour, and the Benefit of the Church they had already done, all thoſe, who had filled the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep</hi> 126.</note> World with Confuſions, and had brought ſuch diviſions into the Church: and he writes to the Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, and almoſt in the ſame words. In his Epiſtle to <hi>Cyriacus,</hi> 
               <note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ep. 143.</note> 
               <hi>I have heard,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Or, <hi>that Dotard,</hi> for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the Dotage of old Age.</note> 
               <hi>that vain Man</hi> Arſacius, <hi>whom the Empreſs has placed in the Epiſcopal Throne, that he has afflicted the Brethren, and the Virgins, who would not Communicate with him; and many of them have died in Priſon for my ſake. For he is a Wolf in Sheeps clothing, and has the Habit of a Biſhop, but is an Adulterer; for as a Woman is called an Adultereſs, who is married to another Man, whilſt her Husband is living, ſo he is not a Carnal but a Spiritual Adulterer; for he has uſurped my See, whilſt I am alive.</hi> It is doubtful, I confeſs, whether this Epiſtle to <hi>Cyriacus</hi> be genuine; for it is rejected both by Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> and Mr. <hi>Boys</hi> in their Notes upon it, and theſe expreſſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Arſacius,</hi> are alledged by Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> as one reaſon, why he thinks it cannot be S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s: but Mr. <hi>Boys</hi> ſays, he ſhould the rather be inclined to think it genuine, becauſe of theſe expreſſions, and he anſwers all the other Objections againſt it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting it himſelf only upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Style. I ſhall only ſay,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57618:11"/> that there are ſo many Accidents, which may make any Authors ſtile different at different times, eſpecially in his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Letters, and thoſe written in Baniſhment, and perhaps under the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders of ſickneſs and dangers, which S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſo often complains of, that this Cenſure from the Stile muſt be the leſs certain, eſpecially ſince <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> could not diſcern but that it was genuine, tho he took notice of this very paſſage concerning <hi>Arſacius</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends it. But ſuppoſe it not to be genuine, yet it is very ancient, and was written probably by one, who lived in S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s time, and was not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with his ſenſe of theſe things.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> having put another Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 148.</note> in mind of the reward, which he would certainly receive for his ſufferings in another World, takes off that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, which might be made from the ſmalneſs of their number; and tells him, that if they would ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves couragious, they would be too hard for thoſe, who were more in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and boaſted themſelves in their wickedneſs; that God would be their help and aſſiſtance, if they would but do their Duty, and that they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in a Cauſe, which concerned all the Churches in the World. But that which yet further ſhews S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 13. <hi>ad O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mp.</hi>
               </note> mind in this matter is; that, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, whom he had Conſecrated and ſent to the <hi>Gothes,</hi> being dead, he takes care to provide another Biſhop for them, and is very ſollicitous, that one ſhould not be Ordained and ſent thither by <hi>Arſacius;</hi> or <hi>Atticus,</hi> ſo that he not only looked upon himſelf as the only rightful Patriarch, but acted as ſuch in his Baniſhment.</p>
            <p>We ſee, that S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> was very far from adviſing, or ſo much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niving at a compliance with the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Biſhop, that had poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf of his See. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, and encouraged thoſe that would not Communicate with him, he comforted them, with the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Rewards in Heaven, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they could ſuffer here in a Cauſe, which was ſo pleaſing to God, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which depended the good of the whole Chriſtian Church; he called <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacius</hi> by name a Wolf in Sheeps clothing, (if the Epiſtle to <hi>Cyriacus</hi> be genuine) and took upon himſelf Epiſcopal Authority, even in his Exile; he encouraged all every where to ſtand out againſt the Uſurper, by his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which he ſent to the Eaſtern Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and to thoſe of the Weſt; to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, who were impriſoned, and to perſons of both Sexes, and of all Orders and Degrees: for the greateſt part of his Epiſtles are upon this Subject, and yet there is not one word of ſubmiſſion or compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; but the moſt earneſt and paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Exhortations to the contrary, from all the motives which he could uſe, that concern either this or another life. And there is much more to the ſame purpoſe in <note n="(g)" place="bottom">Chryſ. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, c. 19. &amp; 23.</note> a Diſcourſe which he wrote in his Exile, to remove the ſcandal ſome took by reaſon of the Perſecution, the Church then lay under.</p>
            <p>The Author of the Preface confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that <hi>the Weſtern Churches did a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 34.</note> 
               <hi>long time refuſe Communion with ſome Biſhops,</hi> that had conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt S. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> He ſhould have ſaid, as <hi>Theodorite,</hi> whom he quotes ſoon after, does, that they would not hold Communion with the Biſhops of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and of the Eaſt, nor with thoſe upon the <hi>Boſphorus,</hi> and of <hi>Thrace,</hi> till they had Regiſtered the name of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> among the reſt of the Patriarchs deceaſed. But he ſays, that <hi>in this caſe the renouncing Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was only, as it were, a breaking off a Correſpondence.</hi> Suppoſe it were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57618:12"/> no more; yet it cannot be ſhown that it was ever thought lawful for one Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch to break off Correſpondence thus with another, but upon ſuch Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s as would juſtifie a ſeparation in Biſhops from their own Patriach. But it was not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rely a not Correſponding with <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſacius</hi> and <hi>Atticus:</hi> for the Weſtern Church not only eſpouſed S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Cauſe, but did approve of the proceedings of thoſe who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for it, and were not backward to declare that they had done well in not Communicating with the new Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sozom. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 26. <hi>Pallad. p.</hi> 214, &amp;c.</note> they denyed that theſe had any Epiſcopal Authority, or ought to be owned as Patriarchs during the life of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>moſt of the Eaſtern Biſhops</hi> would not renounce Communion, though <hi>they would not be acceſſary to that unjuſt Deprivation.</hi> This, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, <hi>Theodorit</hi> ſays: and it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that in the Eaſt many, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for the Juſtice of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Cauſe, and againſt the proceedings of of his Enemies, ſhould be wrought upon by Terrors and Puniſhments; whereas thoſe in the Weſt acted unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly, being under no ſuch hard Circumſtances to awe them to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance. And this makes S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in one of his Epiſtles purpoſely take off that Objection, from the ſmalneſs of their number. But though the Biſhops in the Eaſt did not ſo generally refuſe to Communicate with the Depoſing Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, as they did in the Weſt, yet that very many did refuſe to do it, is evident; for the Priſons were filled with them: and many of theſe who refuſed, were Biſhops of the chiefeſt Sees: for the Biſhops of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> and in general the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſ. Ep.</hi> 26, 27. 126.</note> Biſhops of all <hi>Macedon</hi> were of the number, beſides many others of leſſer Note, or whoſe Sees are not mentioned.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Atticus</hi> at laſt began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr. l</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> or was forced to relax his Rigour, and to Regiſter the name of S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> in the <hi>Diptycks</hi> of the Church, endeavouring by this means to bring over the <hi>Joannites,</hi> as they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, who aſſerted his Cauſe. And when S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> had been ſo long time dead, and this Right had been done to his memory, it is no wonder, that <hi>Atticus</hi> and <hi>Siſinnius</hi> ſhould have the Titles of Patriarchs given them, and that the Council of <hi>Epheſus</hi> ſhould take no notice of the Injuſtice, that S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> had had done him, when both He, and thoſe that had done it were dead, and their names were read together in the Diptycks; when the <hi>Joannites</hi> had had this ſatisfaction given them, and there was no Man now alive, who could pretend any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury done him by the Promotion of the preſent Patriarch, it could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Wiſdom and the Charity of a General Council to revive the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of a thing, which after ſo long a time could admit of no Remedy, but what might be of worſe Conſequence, and might increaſe and prolong the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, which now were much abated, and ſoon after ceaſed.</p>
            <p>The Weſtern Churches had long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 34.</note> the Council of <hi>Epheſus</hi> renewed Communion with the Eaſtern, when once S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s name was written among the names of the other Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs deceaſed. For they never took any notice of <hi>Arſacius</hi> at all, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected all the Meſſages that <hi>Atticus</hi> ſent to get himſelf acknowledged by them, till he had made this amends to the Memory of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> But, as <hi>Theodorite</hi> obſerves, theſe Biſhops, who were thus injurious to S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,</hi> were otherwiſe excellent Men, and there was nothing elſe to be found in them, which might deſerve the Churches Cenſure, and therefore, after the Church had been ſatisfied, as to this matter, they were mentioned with thoſe Titles, that were due to their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57618:12"/> Station, and to their Vertues. For the Titles which <hi>Celeſtine</hi> gives to <hi>Atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc. Epheſ. Part</hi> 1. <hi>col.</hi> 353. 361.</note> and <hi>Siſinnius</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> are only ſuch as ſuppoſe, their names to be written in the Diptycks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the other Patriarchs, and that they were aſſertors of the Catholick Faith: he ſuppoſes <hi>Atticus</hi> at laſt to have been the Rightful Patriarch, and conſequently <hi>Siſinnius,</hi> who ſucceeded him by a Canonical Election, to have been ſo too; and he highly commends both of them for their zeal in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the true Faith, which <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> the next in Succeſſion, had ſo ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betrayed. <hi>Atticus,</hi> after the death of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> and <hi>Siſinnius,</hi> who ſucceeded him, were in their times the only Patriarchs of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and tho <hi>Arſacius</hi> and <hi>Atticus</hi> had not come in regularly, yet it was in the Power of the Church, upon due ſatisfaction made, for the ſake of Peace and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to paſs by ſuch a defect, and diſpenſe with it; and when <hi>Atticus</hi> had Regiſtred S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s name in the Diptycks as Rightful Patriarch, this was in effect to acknowledge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to have been an Uſurper, during his life; which was accepted of by the Church as a ſufficient Declaration of his Repentance: and, as it has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewn, Hereticks themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Repentance were to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not only to Lay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Communion, but according to their Order and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the Church. If our Author could have ſhewn that <hi>Celeſtine</hi> had ſaid as much of <hi>Arſacius,</hi> as he has done of <hi>Atticus</hi> and <hi>Siſinnius,</hi> that had been to his purpoſe, becauſe S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> ſurvived <hi>Arſacius;</hi> but it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, that after the death of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom, Atticus</hi> was at laſt Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Patriarch, and owned by the Weſtern Church for ſuch.</p>
            <p>What is added of <hi>Maximian</hi> and <hi>Proclus</hi> that they were acknowledged as Rightful Patriarchs by the Church, needs no other Anſwer, than what has been already given; for if <hi>Atticus</hi> were Rightful, the reſt who ſucceeded him were ſuch too; if no other excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lay againſt them, than that, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what had been done to S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom.</hi> But beſides, <hi>Maximian</hi> was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc. Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. Part</hi> 3. <hi>col.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> made Patriarch in the room of <hi>Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> in the General Council of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> and this ſurely was enough to purge all defects in the Succeſſion of the Patriarchs of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> For where a General Council does not only approve of, but appoint the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of a Biſhop Depoſed for Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, it can no longer be pretended, that there remains any defect upon the account of injuſtice done to a Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch, who had been ſo long dead; for if the Succeſſion had been interrupted till now from the time that S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> was Depoſed, yet this would put it in its due courſe again. <hi>Proclus</hi> who is next mentioned, and was next in Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to <hi>Maximian,</hi> had been bred up under S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> and could lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſuſpect that he ſhould ever have been reckoned among his uncanonical Succeſſors: for as <hi>Atticus</hi> had inſerted his name among the other Patriarchs, ſo <hi>Proclus</hi> was zealous to make him <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 45.</note> all the further reparation, that could be made, by cauſing his Body to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr'd with all the Honours of a Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſolemnity.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Severianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Gabala,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 4.</note> and <hi>Acacius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Berrhea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afterwards diſcovered to Pope</hi> Innocent, <hi>were neither depoſed, nor reprehended by him:</hi> The reaſon muſt be, that that Pope did not aſſume to himſelf ſo much as his Succeſſors have done, but ſaid he would procure a General Council to be called to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs the Grievances of the <hi>Greck</hi> Church upon this account, and at the ſame time denies all Authority in <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacius,</hi> as being an Intruder. Nay, in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57618:13"/> an <note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Innocentii Epiſt. apud Sozom. lib. 8. c 26.</note> Epiſtle written to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Arcadius,</hi> he Depoſed <hi>Arſacius</hi> after his death, or declared him never to have been Patriarch, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his name to be razed out of the Diptycks; and in the ſame Epiſtle Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated <hi>Arcadius</hi> himſelf, and the Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſs <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> and both De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and Anathematized and Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated <hi>Theophilus</hi> of <hi>Alexandria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not ſuppoſe that this Epiſtle <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Biondell. Pſeudo. Iſid. p.</hi> 562 <hi>Georg. Alex. vit. Chryſ c.</hi> 68 <hi>Mich. Glyc. An. Part</hi> 4 <hi>p.</hi> 259. <hi>Niceph. l.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 34. <hi>Cedren. p.</hi> 332. <hi>Conc. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Col.</hi> 1310.</note> to <hi>Arcadius</hi> deſerves much Credit, for it is rejected by <hi>Blondel,</hi> becauſe <hi>Georgius Alexandrinus</hi> is the firſt that produces it, from whom <hi>Glycas</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> had it, and before them both <hi>Cedrenus</hi> made mention of it. And whereas Pope Innocent in this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, wherein S <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned as already dead, threatens <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxia</hi> the Empreſs with Puniſhments in this World as well as in the World to come, it is noted in the Margin over againſt this Epiſtle in <hi>Labbe</hi>'s Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Councils, that <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> died before S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> which is a plain intimation that the Epiſtle is Spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. But I produce this Epiſtle to obſerve, that if it could paſs for Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ick in the ſeveral Ages in which theſe Authors lived, it is in vain to endeavour to make it be believed, that the Practice of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church was all along ſuch as our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor pretends: for when Men would impoſe any Spurious writing upon the World, they cannot hope to make it be received for genuine, but by giving it as near a Reſemblance to Truth as they can deviſe, and that commonly they do by copying out ſome of the Cuſtoms of their own time; for what Men ſee done in one Age, they are the more eaſily induced to think was done before: but it is too impudent a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery to invent a writing, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains things plainly contrary to the Practice both of their own and all foregoing Ages; a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n can never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be believed in ſuch a Story, or that any will venture to repeat it after him. So that we muſt conclude, that this Epiſtle was agreeable to the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Church in <hi>Georgius Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus</hi>'s time, who lived in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Century, and that <hi>Glycas</hi> in the twelfth, and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> in the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth ſaw nothing abſurd in it: but as <hi>Blondel</hi> has obſerved, that part of it, which concerns the Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Eudoxia</hi> is not mentioned by <hi>Cedrenus,</hi> which makes him ſuſpect it was foiſted in after his time: for all Forgeries as they are deſigned commonly to ſerve ſome turn or other, ſo they ſeldom fail to be ſuited to the abuſes of the times in which they are made.</p>
            <p>But it is confeſſed that not only Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> but the whole Weſtern Church did refuſe Communion with the Depoſing Biſhops, and it is further obſervable, that when, after the death of <hi>Flavianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch,</hi> who had not conſented to the Depoſing of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom, Porphyrius</hi> ſuceeeded <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sozom. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 29.</note> him, who agreed to it, many of <hi>Syria</hi> broke off Communion with that Church.</p>
            <p>Our Author next obſerves, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 5, 6.</note> whereas <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> in the ſecond Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſus</hi> abſolved <hi>Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yches,</hi> and Depoſed <hi>Flavianus,</hi> and then mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered him, and Conſecrated <hi>Anatolius</hi> in his room: <hi>none of thoſe Biſhops, who concurred and acted with</hi> Dioſcorus <hi>in the unjuſt ejectment of</hi> Flavianus, <hi>and the unlawful Ordination of</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolius
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57618:13"/> 
               <hi>in his place, were rejected in the fourth General Council of</hi> Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon, <hi>only</hi> Eutyches <hi>and</hi> Dioſcorus. <hi>that perſiſted in their Hereſie. For that Holy Synod concerned not it ſelf about the Ordinations of uncanonical and illegal Patriarchs, but only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of every one the Profeſſion of the Orthodox Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this repreſentation of the Caſe, he would have it believed, that no Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection was made againſt the Biſhops, who concurred with <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> in the ſecond Council of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> for having concurred with him; but that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Orthodox Faith was only required of them, and ſo they were forthwith received by the Council. Which is ſo far from being true, that tho they had owned their fault in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing <hi>Flavianus</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Dorylaeum,</hi> and were as forward as any to make Profeſſion of the true Faith, yet it was moved in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> by the Judges, or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers ſent by the Emperour to inſpect and regulate the Proceedings there, that <hi>Juvenalis</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem, Thalaſſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia, Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ancyra, Euſtathius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Berytus,</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Seleucia</hi> in <hi>Iſauria,</hi> 
               <note n="(i)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Conc. Chalced. Act. 1. Col 323. Euagr. lib. 2. c. 18. p. 313.</note> ſhould be put under the ſame Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> and ſhould according to the Canons be deprived of their See's: which was aſſented to by the Biſhops of the Eaſt, who ſaid it was a <hi>juſt</hi> 
               <note n="(k)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ib. Conc. Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Euagr. ib.</note> 
               <hi>Sentence;</hi> they agreed that it was juſt to reject thoſe Biſhops, whoſe names I have now recited, and who are the ſame, that on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Author by name ſets down as not rejected in the fourth General Council, only he has left out <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ancyra,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted <hi>Photius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Iſauria</hi> in <hi>Epirus,</hi> or, as the Publiſher has Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected it, <hi>Photius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tyre.</hi> If he means, they were not finally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, he ſays true, but then he ought not to have concealed, that they were not received in the firſt <hi>Actions</hi> of that Council, nor upon what grounds they were at laſt admitted; but theſe are ſuch as will not be at all ſerviceable to his Cauſe. They took their places in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed among the reſt of the Biſhops at the opening of the Council, but ſo did <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> himſelf too, tho it was objected againſt by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Legats, who were over-ruled, it being thought reaſonable that they ſhould retain their Places till their Cauſe was heard; for to diſplace them before might ſeem to be a Prejudging them. But upon examination it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, that the caſe of theſe Biſhops could deſerve nothing but commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Council: ſome of them, S. <hi>Baſil</hi> of <hi>Seleucia</hi> by name, had <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc. Chald. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 137. 229.</note> made profeſſion of the true Faith in the Synod of <hi>Epheſus</hi> it ſelf, wherein <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> preſided; and at laſt what they did in concurrence with him, was by compulſion: for they were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with armed Soldiers, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered violence to them, and forced them to Subſcribe a Blank Paper, which was afterwards filled up; <note n="(l)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Euagr. ib. p. 311. Conc. Chald. Act. 1. Col 129. 251.</note> as they pleaded for themſelves, and as <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> Biſhop of <note n="(m)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (Dio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.) Euagr. p 314 Con. Chal Act. 3. Col. 382.</note> 
               <hi>Dorylaeum</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57618:14"/> teſtified. So that when this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair came again under debate, the Council was very compaſſionate to theſe offending Biſhops, in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the hard Circumſtances, in which the Offence <note n="(n)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nc, Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ced. Act.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 509. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. ib. p.</hi> 324.</note> was committed; and therefore they deſired that they might be ſuffered to receive <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Five Biſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as Members of the Council, and the Emperour being firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with their requeſt, by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion they were reſtored.</p>
            <p>What then can we conclude from hence more than that the Authority of a General Council may be ſufficient upon ſo reaſonable Motives to reſtore Biſhops, who by the Canons have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eited their Sees? But it is a very wrong account of this matter, to ſay barely, that <hi>none of thoſe Biſhops were re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ected in the fourth General Council of</hi> Chalcedon: for they were rejected at firſt, or elſe there would have been no debate concerning their Caſe, when once they would Subſcribe the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Faith; but tho they profered to do this, they had like to have lain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame condemnation with <hi>Dioſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corus,</hi> ſo far as it concerned his being Depoſed from his See: and it was upon conſiderations peculiar to their Caſe, and which in all equity ought to be admitted of in abatement to the Rigour of the Letter of the Canons, that they were at laſt accepted: for if there had been no more in their Caſe than what our Author has thought fit to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, they had, as it appears, been abſolutely rejected.</p>
            <p>But he ſays, that <hi>Anatolius</hi> was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canonically advanced to the See of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> and the Synod concerned not it ſelf about ſuch Matters, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring only of every one the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Orthodox Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſeems to ſuppoſe here, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olius</hi> was conſtituted Patriarch by <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> in the ſecond Council of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus</hi> in the room of <hi>Flavianus;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Liberat. Breviar. c.</hi> 12.</note> which cannot be true; for he was not Patriarch till after the death of <hi>Flavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus,</hi> and <hi>Flavianus</hi> died in Priſon after the Synod. If it had been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>Leo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> could not have been uncertain, as he writes to <note n="(o)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>De Ordinatione ejus, qui Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinopolitanae Eccleſiae coepit praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere nihil interim in alterutram par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem temerè reſcribendum putavi, non dilectionem negans, ſed manifeſtatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Catholicae veritatis expectans.</hi> Epiſt. Leon. ad Theodoſ. Conc. Chalc. Col. 59.</note> 
               <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> he was, whether the Promotion of <hi>Anatolius</hi> were uncano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical or no; it being notorious that all muſt be uncanonical, which was done in prejudice to an Orthodox Patriarch's Right, by an Heretical Biſhop in an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Synod: And beſides, if he had been made Patriarch in the ſecond Council of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he had been De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> in which himſelf preſided: for all the Acts of that <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Epheſus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euagr. ib. p.</hi> 328.</note> are declared void in the General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> excepting only the Ordination of <hi>Maximus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe this Author ſays, that <hi>that Holy Synod concerned not it ſelf about the Ordinations of uncanonical and illegal Patriarchs.</hi> I ſhall bring a remarkable inſtance to ſhew, that that Council did concern it ſelf about uncanonical Ordinations, which may convince us, that if <hi>Anatolius</hi> had been uncanonically Ordained, it would have been inſiſted upon: For there was at that time a conteſt between <hi>Baſſianus</hi> and <hi>Stephanus</hi> concerning the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> and the Council upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57618:14"/> examination finding that the Pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of both of them were contrary to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc. Chal. Act.</hi> 11, 12.</note> the Canons, Depoſed them both and appointed a third Biſhop to be Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, tho <hi>Baſſianus</hi> had been in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of that See four years; which ſhews how little our Author's Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were thought of in that Council. And to make it yet further manifeſt, how little this Author knew of the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> when he ſays, that <hi>only</hi> Eutyches <hi>and</hi> Dioſcorus <hi>were rejected there, who perſiſted in their Hereſie: Anatolius</hi> expreſly declared in the Council, that <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> was not Depoſed for Hereſie, but becauſe he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euagr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap</hi> 18. <hi>p.</hi> 327.</note> had Excommunicated <hi>Leo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and had refuſed to appear, when he was thrice ſummoned.</p>
            <p>The next Inſtances, which he brings, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 6.</note> are in Reign of the Emperour <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatius,</hi> who, he ſays, Depoſed three Patriarchs of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which when he proceeds to give an account of, he inſiſts upon his Depoſing of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemius</hi> and <hi>Macedonius</hi> only, ſaying that <hi>the great</hi> Elias <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>imbraced the Communion of all theſe three Patriarchs, when all were alive together,</hi> that is, he embraced the Communion of <hi>Euphemius, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonius,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus,</hi> the two laſt being preferred to that See contrary to the Canons; but if <hi>Timotheus</hi> was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canonically Depoſed too, as he ſaid, why did he not inform us how he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved himſelf towards his Succeſſor? tho indeed it is to little purpoſe to concern our ſelves what uncanonical Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops did: for they could have no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to break off Communion from their Succeſſors, who came in by as good a Right, as they had done them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>However he tells us, that when <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atius</hi> had Depoſed <hi>Euphemius,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not embrace the Hereſie of the <hi>Acephali,</hi> and Anathematize the the fourth General Council, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with <hi>Severus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> and had ſet up <hi>Macedonius,</hi> in his room; <hi>Euphemius</hi> did not depart from the Communion of his unlawful Succeſſor, becauſe he held the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith; and ſo likewiſe that <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donius,</hi> when he was Depoſed for the ſame Reaſons, held Communion with <hi>Timotheus,</hi> who ſucceeded him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was Orthodox. He ſays that <hi>Elias</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> held Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in like manner with all theſe three Patriarchs, and that when the ſame Emperour had Depoſed and Baniſhed the ſaid <hi>Elias,</hi> becauſe he would not be brought over to his Heretical Opinions, and conſtituted <hi>John</hi> in his place, <hi>Elias</hi> continued Communion with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he proved Orthodox, as did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the two famous Monks <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Sabas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, it does not appear, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Euphemius</hi> did Communicate with his two Succeſſors or not; but it is this Authors cuſtom to make his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the ſilence of Hiſtorians, and to conclude that the Depoſed Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops did Communica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> only becauſe the Hiſtorians do not poſitively ſay the contrary, whereas no ſuch thing ought to be concluded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as I ſhall afterwards ſhew. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d it is not p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>obable that <hi>Eup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> did Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with <hi>Macedonius:</hi> for <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemius</hi> had lately aſſembled a Synod purpoſely to confirm the fourth Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council, whereas <hi>Macedonius</hi> Subſcribed <hi>Zeno</hi>'s Henoticon, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of which was to lay aſide the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the fourth General Council, which was next to the condemning it.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Euphemius</hi> did Communicate with both his Succeſſors, as <hi>Cyrillus</hi> of <hi>Scythopolis</hi> informs us, <hi>Elias</hi> did; yet if we conſider the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Circumſtances of that time, and the peculiar Reaſons, that might induce them both to it, this will not prove the general Aſſertion, which this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57618:15"/> Author lays down, <hi>That not one of thoſe Biſhops that were unjuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, did ever ſeparate himſelf from the Communion of the Church, upon the account of his being dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed, provided that he that was uncano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y promoted after him, was Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox.</hi> But this will only be an Exception to the general Practice, and ſo will prove the quite contrary, to what he would prove by it.</p>
            <p>The Church at that time was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sabae Vit. per Cyrill. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ythop. c.</hi> 50. <hi>Euagr. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 30.</note> over-run with Hereſies and Schiſms; and the Emperor himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a zealous Heretick, the Othodox Biſhops we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e forced to be contented to ſubmit to great Inconveniencies, and not to inſiſt upon their Right and Authority, ſo they could but ſecure an Orthodox Succeſſion in their Sees; they ſaw, it was impoſſible for them to keep in themſelves, and the next thing they deſired was to have an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Succeſſor, who probably never would have been prevailed with to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Throne, without the rightful Patriarchs conſent, and when he was in it, ſtill owned the former, as him who had the juſt Title to it: Which might make <hi>Euphemius,</hi> when he was to be ſent into Baniſhment, deſire that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonius</hi> would undertake for his ſafe conduct; and when <hi>Macedonius,</hi> by the Emperors leave, went to give him aſſurance of it, he commanded his Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodor. Lect. l.</hi> 2.</note> firſt to take off his Epiſcopal Robe, and ſo he went into the Baptiſtry to <hi>Euphemius;</hi> and beſides borrowed Money to preſent him with for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Attendants. This is a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient evidence both of his reſpect for <hi>Euphemius,</hi> and of his acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to have the Authority ſtill, notwithſtanding his own advancement to the See. And in theſe Caſes it was ſcarce greater force upon the Biſhop that was depoſed, than upon him that was promoted; but they by conſent did what they ſaw moſt advantageous for the Church i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe difficult Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, thinking it no time for the Orthodox to divide from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when their Number was ſo ſmall in compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſon of the Hereticks, who had a zealous Emperor at the head of them.</p>
            <p>The caſe was the ſame in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vit. Sabae, c.</hi> 56.</note> of <hi>Elias</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; John,</hi> his Succeſſor, had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Emperor to anathematize the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> but was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon by the Orthodox, to make profeſſion of the True Faith; for which he was caſt into Priſon, and was to have been baniſhed, but the <hi>Sabas</hi> and the reſt of the Monks petitioned the Emperor to keep him in the See, knowing that it was impoſſible to get <hi>Elias</hi> reſtored, and that if <hi>John</hi> were caſt out for being Orthodox, the next in Succeſſion muſt of conſequence be an Heretick.</p>
            <p>This then only proves, that there has been ſuch a Caſe, when, to prevent Hereſies in the Church, Biſhops have reſigned their Sees, or at leaſt have conſented that others ſhould ſucceed them; but this is ſo far from being an Argument, that in all Caſes, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their conſent, an Uſurper ought to be communicated with, in prejudice to the Authority of the true Biſhop, that it plainly proves the contrary. St. <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> for the like Reaſons reſigned the Biſhoprick of <hi>C. P.</hi> ſaying, that he was contented to be the <hi>Jonas,</hi> who ſhould be thrown over-board, to all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the Storms that threatned the Church: But can we from hence conclude, that <hi>Nectarius,</hi> his Succeſſor, would have been owned by the Church as Patriarch of <hi>C. P.</hi> if St. <hi>Gregory</hi> had not reſigned? Or muſt we not rather conclude, that the Church would never have acknowledged him. And like this ſeems to have been the Caſe of the <hi>Jews</hi> under the <hi>Romans;</hi> the High Prieſt by right of Succeſſion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57618:15"/> receding, and being glad upon any terms to preſerve the true Religion and Worſhip of God, rather than with the whole Jewiſh Nation to be deprived of it, under Heathen Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</p>
            <p>Hitherto our Author has ſpoken only of the Patriarchs of <hi>C. P.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting that he occaſionally mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Meletius</hi> upon the account of St. <hi>Chryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtom</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> on occaſion of <hi>Euphemius.</hi> But after he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thus far, he takes a large ſtep back again to inform us, that St. <hi>Cyrill,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> came into that See contrary to the Canons, being by <hi>Arians</hi> put into the room of <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> who was thruſt out, for having taken part with St. <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> Now St. <hi>Cyrill,</hi> ſays he, was, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon his Converſion to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Faith, acknowledged for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and even <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus</hi> himſelf did not withdraw from <hi>Cyrill</hi>'s Communion.</p>
            <p>For the proof of all this, he refers to the Life of St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> whereas <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vit. Athan. p.</hi> 48.</note> the Author of his Life only ſays that <hi>Acacius</hi> and <hi>Patrophilus</hi> thruſt <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> out of the See of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and placed <hi>Cyrill</hi> there, but ſays nothing of <hi>Maximus</hi>'s holding Communion with <hi>Cyrill</hi> afterwards: Yet he ſaying nothing to the contrary, our Author takes it for granted, that <hi>Maximus</hi> did communicate with <hi>Cyrill;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he mentioning <hi>Maximus</hi> upon the account only of St. <hi>Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> had no occaſion to take any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notice either of him, or of <hi>Cyrill,</hi> than St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was concerned in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 38.</note> it.</p>
            <p>I confeſs <hi>Socrates</hi> agrees with this anonymous Authour of the Life of St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in relating that <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> was turned out of his Biſhoprick <note place="margin">Hieron. in Chron.</note> by <hi>Acacius</hi> and <hi>Patrophilus</hi> to make way for <hi>Cyrill:</hi> But St. <hi>Hierom</hi> on the contrary ſays, that <hi>Maximus</hi> was dead before St. <hi>Cyrill</hi> came into his See; and <hi>Theodorite,</hi> 
               <note n="(p)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theod. lib 2 c. 2.</note> that <hi>Maximus</hi> being tranſlated to an immortal Life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Cyrill</hi> ſucceeded him, who was a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous defender of the Catholick Faith; and to put this matter out of all di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, beſides St. <hi>Hierom</hi> and <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> we have the expreſs Teſtimony of the <note n="(q)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Synod. Ep. Conc. <hi>C. P.</hi> apud Theod. lib. 5. c. 9.</note> General Council of <hi>C. P.</hi> that he came in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nonically, being ordained by the Biſhops of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and had in divers places ſignal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed himſelf in maintaining the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith againſt the <hi>Arians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there being one <hi>Cyrill</hi> an <hi>Arian,</hi> who, ſoon after <hi>Maximus,</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and was the next Biſhop but one to St. <hi>Cyrill,</hi> the great Uncertainty and Confuſion that there is in the Catalogue of the Biſhops of this See at that time, as may be ſeen by comparing the different accounts of their Names in St. <hi>Hierom, Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hieron. in Chron. Epiphan. Haer.</hi> 66. <hi>Niceph.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Nicephorus;</hi> might eaſily occaſion the Aſperſions, which have been caſt upon this Father by ſome Writers, who ſuppoſed St. <hi>Cyrill</hi> the <hi>Arian</hi> was that <hi>Cyrill,</hi> who was next in Succeſſion to <hi>Maximus.</hi> But it is abundantly <note n="*" place="margin">See the Life of S. <hi>Cyrill,</hi> by Dr. <hi>Cave.</hi>
               </note> ſufficient in his Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that a general Council by their united Suffrages have atteſted both to his being Orthodox, and to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicalneſs of his Conſecration. But I muſt not omit here to take notice, that tho <hi>Socrates</hi> and the Author of the Life of St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> do both ſay, that <hi>Cyrill</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:57618:16"/> by Uſurpation, during the Life of <hi>Maximus;</hi> yet they mention this as done under <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and it is a Miſtake peculiar to our Author to place it under the Reign of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, in contradiction to all Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>The Author now returns again to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and ſays that when <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychius</hi> was depoſed from that See, and <hi>John</hi> preferred to it, in the Reign of <hi>Juſtinian, Eutychius</hi> continued to communicate with <hi>John:</hi> Which he could bring no Proof of, but there is undeniable Proof of the contrary. For <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> who was an Eye Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to all this buſineſs, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Attendant upon <hi>Eutychius</hi> 
               <note n="(r)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Subjecit omnes canonicis paenis, donec reſipiſcerent.</hi> Vit. Eutychii c. 5. Auctore Euſtathio Presbytero, Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtico familiari.</note>, has left it written in his Life, that <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychius</hi> pronounced Excommunication againſt the Synod, which was called to depoſe him, till they ſhould repent of it, and reſtore him.</p>
            <p>All that he ſays concerning <hi>Anthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Sergius,</hi> and others, whoſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinations, tho they were Hereticks, were allowed of as valid, needs no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, enough having been already ſaid on that Point, in the Caſe of <hi>Mele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Callinicus,</hi> he acquaints us, after he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 10.</note> was depoſed by <hi>Juſtinian Rhinotme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> did not depart from the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> who was appointed his Succeſſor. He might as well have ſaid, that <hi>Callinicus</hi> ſaw and converſed with <hi>Cyrus,</hi> after the loſs of his Eyes, when he was as far from him as <hi>Rome</hi> is from <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> For this had <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cedren. p.</hi> 446. <hi>Theophan. p.</hi> 313. <hi>Niceph. Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nop. p.</hi> 28.</note> been more agreable to the way of writing Legends, and has altogether as much foundation in Hiſtory as that. For the Hiſtorians only ſay, that the Emperor cauſed his Eyes to be put out, and then baniſhed him to <hi>Rome,</hi> but what became of him there, or with whom he communicated, they do not inform us.</p>
            <p>The next Inſtance which he dwells <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 11.</note> longer upon, than any other in his whole Treatiſe, is nothing at all to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For what if <hi>Theodorus Studites</hi> were in fault for ſeparating from the Patriarchs <hi>Taraſius</hi> and <hi>Nicepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> becauſe they had admitted <hi>Joſeph</hi> the Steward of the Church to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, who had officiated in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Marriage? How does this prove, that <hi>although a Biſhop was unjuſtly deprived, neither he nor the Church ever made a Separation, if the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor was not an Heretick?</hi> Were <hi>Taraſius</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> Intruders? Or did <hi>Theodorus</hi> ſeparate upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count? No ſuch thing is pretended; but <hi>Joſeph</hi> had been guilty of a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and wicked Action<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet was ſuffered to continue in Communion, and hereupon <hi>Theodorus</hi> withdraws himſelf from the Church, for which he is blamed, and very juſtly: But this only ſhews, that private Chriſtians ought not to forſake the Church, tho the Diſcipline of it ſhould not be ſo duly adminiſtred as they could wiſh, but muſt take care of their own Duty, tho the Church Governours ſhould be negligent of theirs.</p>
            <p>After ſo much ſaid in ſo ſhort a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 17.</note> Book beſide the Subject, he at laſt comes again to the Point, but falls upon ſuch an Example as is alone e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to diſparage his whole Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, with any one almoſt, that has ever heard of the Names of <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Photius.</hi> For what can be more notorious than that <hi>Ignatius</hi> did not Communicate with <hi>Photius,</hi> after he was diſplaced, and <hi>Photius</hi> got into the See? can we imagin he Communicated with one, by whom he ſtood himſelf Excommunicated? with one, who was Excomunicated by his beſt Friend and Advocate Pope <hi>Nicholas?</hi> and who in return had Excommunicated the ſaid
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57618:16"/> Pope? <note n="(s)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Conc. Conſtantinopol. 4. Col. 1268.</note> For <hi>Photius</hi> had not been Conſecrated forty days before he openly Depoſed and Anathematiſed <hi>Ignatius,</hi> as we have it related in an account, that <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſent to Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him how <hi>Photius</hi> had dealt with him. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was ſoon after ſent into <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nicet. vit. Ignat. p.</hi> 1222.</note> Baniſhment, where he was kept under ſo cloſe Confinement, that he was not ſuffered to perform any part of his Function, and as he was not allowed to ſtir out, ſo no body was permitted to come to him. And if there be any thing of certainty in all the Hiſtory of thoſe affairs, nothing can be more certain, than that <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Photius</hi> did not hold Communion with each other, for nothing occurs more frequently than the <hi>Anathema's,</hi> which they pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced one againſt the other.</p>
            <p>But all the Reaſon our Author ſeems to have in this and ſome other Inſtances, to conclude that the Depoſed Patriarch did not refuſe Communion with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truder, is becauſe both their names were read in the Diptycks: whereas this one inſtance of <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Photius</hi> is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to convince us that this is no good Argument: for it is certain that theſe two Biſhops did not hold Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with one another; &amp; yet after theſe differences were compoſed, which had been occaſioned in the Church by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up <hi>Photius,</hi> both their names were Recorded in the Diptycks; and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly neither Party being to be wrought upon to recede from their Pretenſions in behalf of the Patriarch, whoſe Right they had maintained, this was found to be the only Expedient, to do the ſame honour, to both of them, which might without difficulty be agreed to, ſince the Synod, which reſtored <hi>Photius</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> had cancelled all the Acts, againſt <hi>Photius,</hi> of that Council which Depoſed him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored <hi>Ignatius:</hi> and this Council which reſtored <hi>Photius,</hi> is by the <hi>Greeks</hi> reckoned the eighth General Council.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Depoſing of <hi>Photius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 18, 19.</note> a ſecond time, and the Depoſing of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas, Zonaras,</hi> whom our Author <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zon. Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 113.</note> quotes, ſays nothing, from which it may be collected that <hi>Photius</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Communion with <hi>Stephen,</hi> and <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> with <hi>Euthymius,</hi> who were put into their rooms. But becauſe <hi>Zona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> ſays nothing to the contrary, he concludes, that they did hold Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them, which is a very falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious way of arguing, to make Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences from a Negative, without any other Reaſon or Circumſtance; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in ſo ſhort an account as <hi>Zonaras</hi> gives of theſe things, who only ſays, in as few words, as he can well expreſs himſelf in, that the Emperour picking a quarrel with the Patriarch ſent him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Monaſtery, and appointed his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Stephen</hi> to be Patriarch; and that <hi>Nicholas</hi> was likewiſe put into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery; and <hi>Euthymius</hi> conſtituted Patriarch in his ſtead. And the ſame Author in S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Caſe takes no notice of that ſeparation, which was occaſioned by his Baniſhment, for thirty five years together in the Church, which the more ancient Hiſtorians inlarge ſo much upon, and ſet forth in ſo many particulars. And to be convinced that nothing ought to be concluded from the ſilence, eſpecially of theſe latter Hiſtoriars and Annaliſts, we need only compare what theſe write, with the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count which <hi>Theodorite,</hi> and <hi>Socrates,</hi> and <hi>Sozomen</hi> give of the ſame Actions, and when it is notorious, that they commonly omit things as material as thoſe they take notice of, nothing more need be ſaid to ſhew, how little regard is to be had to their omiſſion of things; it is well if we may depend upon what they relate, but to ſay ſuch a thing never was, becauſe they do not relate it, is ſuch a way of arguing as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57618:17"/> only betrays the weakneſs of the Cauſe, and ſhews how great want there is of better Arguments.</p>
            <p>And as for the Ordinations of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thymius,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 20.</note> which he ſays, were not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected after <hi>Nicholas</hi> was reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I have ſhewn how inſignificant an Argument that is, when even after He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks were received into the Church upon their Converſion, their Orders were not diſallowed.</p>
            <p>But his account of <hi>Coſmas Atticus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is the boldeſt ſtroke we have had yet, for, when <hi>Nicetas Choniates,</hi> whoſe Authority he alledges. ſays in expreſs terms, <note n="(t)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Nice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Choniat. de Imperat. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nuel. lib 2. p. 54.</note> that he Excommunicated ſome of the Courtiers, and the Synod too, which Depoſed him, this Author has the confidence to quote <hi>Nicetas</hi> to vouch for him, that <hi>Coſmas Atticus</hi> never ſeparated from the Communion of his Depoſers. But we have had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience enough of our Author by this time, not to wonder much now at whatever he is pleaſed to ſay.</p>
            <p>Of the Depoſing the Patriarchs <hi>Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>Camaterus,</hi> and <hi>Nicetas,</hi> we have only a bare Narrative in <hi>Nicetas Chonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> but upon the Promotion of <hi>Doſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi> in the room of <hi>Leontius,</hi> he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſays, that the chief Biſhops, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon his Tranſlation from <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to be contrary to the Canons, <note n="(u)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. id de Jaac. lib<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. p. p 260.</note> held ſeparate Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies.</p>
            <p>Our Author has obſerved that in the ſpace of nine years the Emperour <hi>Iſaacius Angelus</hi> made five Patriarchs ſucceſſively, who were all alive toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but he might have ſpared his <hi>Admiration, that they did not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from one anothers Communion:</hi> for if this had been the approved and conſtant Practice of the Church as he pretends, what great matter of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration could it be, that five Patriarchs ſhould do as all their Predeceſſors had done in the like Caſe? B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the only wonder is, how this Author comes to know, that they did not ſeparate, when the Hiſtorian, whom he quotes, ſays no ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>It is plain indeed; that if the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour had but any pretence (and it was hard if he could find none) the <hi>Greek</hi> Church in theſe Ages was ſo low, and the Clergy of ſo baſe and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Spirits, that they were prepared to comply with any thing: and if they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed their Reſentments it was in ſuch a manner, as could become the Zeal only of theſe degenerate times. Thus when <hi>Euthymius</hi> was Depoſed, to make <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cedren. p.</hi> 607.</note> way for the Reſtauration of <hi>Nicholas</hi> to his See again, the Clergy, who were of <hi>Nicholas</hi>'s Party, fell upon <hi>Euthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi> like mad Men, and beat him with their Fiſts, and plucked him by the Beard, and flung him down, calling him Uſurper, and Adulterer: and if it ſhould be granted that Men who could ſhew ſuch barbarous uſage, ſhould notwithſtanding keep in Communion with the Uſurper, whom they could think to deſerve ſuch uſage from them; I ſuppoſe their examp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e will be thought of no better Authority in the one than in the other.</p>
            <p>But upon the whole matter, after a full examination of all the Inſtances, which this Author has brought to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Aſſertion; I muſt conclude in contradiction to it, that very few, if any, Examples can be produced of Biſhops, who were unjuſtly Depoſed, that did hold Communion with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truders; and that therefore upon the account of any thing, which is offered in this Treatiſe, a Separation is not Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57618:17"/>
            <head>REMARKS UPON THE <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Edition.</head>
            <p>SInce my writing this, I have met with the Greek and Latin Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Author, and beſides Mr. <hi>Hody</hi>'s Preface, there are ſome few things in the Book it ſelf further to be obſerved.</p>
            <p>In the Engliſh Preface to this Treatiſe we are told, that <hi>there is no Name prefixt before it; nor any Characters in it that may</hi> lead, <hi>us to a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conjecture; about the Author:</hi> But Mr. <hi>Hody,</hi> in his Preface to the Greek and Latin Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thinks he has diſcovered the Author to be <hi>Nicephorus Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtus;</hi> that which he grounds his Conjecture upon is, that this Diſcourſe is in the ſame Volume with ſeveral other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcripts, which have the Name of <hi>Nicephorus Calliſtus</hi> to them, but he does not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us that this is written in the ſame hand with the reſt, nor that it has the leaſt Connexion or Affinity with them; nor that all the other Tracts in that Volume have his Name before them; and when the other Treatiſes have his Name prefixed, and this has it not, it is moſt probable that this is not his; for if it were, it would bear his Name as well as the reſt: Indeed, if ſome of the moſt remarkable Tracts only had his Name to them, and others, which were known to be his, were among them without his Name, it would not be unlikely that this might be his too; but when the reſt have his Name, and this has none, what can be more reaſonably concluded from it, than that there was as much cauſe why his Name ſhould be omitted in this, as why it was pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>xt before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt? Mr. <hi>Hody</hi> himſelf obſerves, that there is no e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ct agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Catalogue of the Patriarchs of <hi>C. P.</hi> by <hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57618:18"/> and the account of them in this Author. But there is a much greater and more obvious Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them than that, for <hi>Nicephorus Calliſtus</hi> writes in an eaſie flowing ſtile, and with great Elegancy, conſidering the Age in which he wrote; but our Author is heavy and unpleaſant, and ſcarce able to expreſs that little he has to ſay; and the beſt thing that can be ſaid of his ſtile is, that it is as good as the Subject deſerves, and it is great pity that ſuch Stuff ſhould be put into any better Language. But there is another Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two Authors yet more remarkable; for <hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus,</hi> giving an account of <note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Niceph. lib. 13. cap. 20.</note> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s parting Words to his Friends, makes their holding Communion with the ſucceeding Biſhop to depend wholly upon his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; he ſays, that St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> did an extraordinary thing, which was without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and had ſomething more than Humane in it, when he gave leave to his Friends to live in communion with Biſhops, by whom he had been ſo ill uſed: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as our Author makes it not to depend upon any Permiſſion of the rightful Biſhop, but to be the conſtant practice of the Church, and the indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable Duty of all Chriſtians to ſubmit to every Intruder, if he be no Heretick.</p>
            <p>But if there were as much reaſon to believe that <hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus Calliſtus</hi> was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Treatiſe, as there is to think that he was not, yet his Name would give no great Credit to it, but a Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion rather, that it is not to be credited: For, except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Malela,</hi> lately publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Hody,</hi> there is ſcarce any Author more fabulous than <hi>Nicephorus.</hi> But this Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript outgoes even <hi>Malela,</hi> and may have the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of being the worſt Greek Author extant, 'till Mr. <hi>Hody</hi> is pleaſed to publiſh ſome other.</p>
            <p>Both the Latin and the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Preface ſuppoſe this Tract to have been a Sermon or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, or at leaſt, as it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Latin, to have been a Lecture in the Schools of ſome Profeſſor of Hiſtory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in two places he beſpeaks his Auditor, and not his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. I have no mind to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Controverſie about a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57618:18"/> thing of no moment, but this Reaſon does not ſatisfie me; for I find that <note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Epiph. Her. 64. n. 5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ib. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Epiph. de Menſur. Ponderib. n. 2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ib. n. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Epiphanius</hi> addreſſes himſelf to his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in his Book againſt Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, tho no Man can therefore imagin, that that Book conſiſts of as many Homilies, as he treats of Hereſies; and he writes in the ſame manner in his Book of <hi>Meaſures and Weights,</hi> tho it appears, that that Book was neither an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, nor a Lecture. I rather believe, that Copies of Books being dear and ſcarce, before the Invention of Printing, it was cuſtomary to recite other Diſcourſes as well as Homilies or Lectures, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch Expreſſions might either be uſed at firſt by the Author, or be afterwards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by him that recited it. Beſides, the ſtile of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe does not ſeem at all like to that of an Homily; for their Homilies, after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Learning, were full of Hyperboles, Anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſes, Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tologies, and frequent Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of the ſame Words, and all the Affectations of a falſe Eloquence; but our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor uſes few Words, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſhew of Eloquence, or pretence to it; for to do him right, he ſeems to have underſtood his own Talent better, than to pretend to any thing in that way.</p>
            <p>Having ſaid thus much of the Author, Mr. <hi>Hody</hi> comes now to give an account of his Reaſons for the Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and here he informs his Reader in very tragical Terms, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> being all in Flames, he, for our comfort, has found out this new Engine to quench the Fire. I deſire to be as apprehenſive of the Miſchiefs of Schiſm as any Man, and therefore muſt beſeech all Chriſtians ſeriouſly to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whether this Treatiſe be not more likely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Schiſms in the Church, than to prevent or remove them.</p>
            <p>His next buſineſs is to ſet down ſome Examples from Antiquity, which he puts our preſent Biſhops in mind, it is their duty to follow. The firſt is that of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> but he has ſaid no more of him than we had before in the Engliſh Preface, excepting that he has framed a new Speech for him; which makes me begin to ſuſpect that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps <hi>Palladius</hi> took the ſame
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57618:19"/> liberty, that Mr. <hi>Hody</hi> has done; for Declamations are as uſual and altogether as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in a Dialogue as in a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</p>
            <p>His next Inſtance is of St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>African</hi> Biſhops in the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at <hi>Carthage</hi> 
               <note n="(c)" place="bottom">lib. de Geſtis cum eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito.</note>. The account S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> gives us is this, that before they held this Conference with the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, the Catholick Biſhops made a Propoſal, that if the Donatiſts could convince them, that they were in the wrong, they would be contented to be received by the Donatiſts, not as Biſhops, but to Lay-Communion only, as private Chriſtians; but the Donatiſt Biſhops, if they were convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of Error, ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, upon their Repentance, to preſide in the ſame Sees together with the Catholick Biſhops, and the Survivors to be the ſole Biſhops of the Sees; or if it would not be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of, that there ſhould be two Biſhops at once of the ſame Church; that both the Catholick and Donatiſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſhould reſign, and that new Biſhops ſhould be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in all ſuch Churches, where the Donatiſts had their Biſhops, as well as the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks. And St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſays, that of almoſt Three Hundred Biſhops, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re were but Two who made any ſcruple or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur upon it, all beſides were earneſt and zealous for this Expedient; and theſe Two were ſoon brought over to be of the ſame mind with the reſt. This is the full of what St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> relates, and I need not tell the Reader, tho I muſt tell Mr. <hi>Hody,</hi> that it is nothing to the preſent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: But it is obſervable that the Schiſmatical Biſhops were ſo refractory in the Conference at <hi>Carthage,</hi> that they gave little encouragement for the Rightful Biſhops to make any ſuch Propoſals to Intruders afterwards.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi>'s Caſe has been ſpoken to already: And as for the Advice which St. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> gave to <hi>Novatian,</hi> when he pretended that he was unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly made Biſhop, <hi>that this would be beſt ſeen by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting from his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation;</hi> it is admirable Advice, and I hope, all will take notice of it, who are concerned.</p>
            <p>Another Citation he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces from the firſt I piſtle of St. <hi>Clement</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to ſhew, that that Father ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the Presbyters, who were ordained by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles themſelves, rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede from their Right, when they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urned out by a Faction; than to occaſion any
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57618:19"/> Diviſion in the Church. But it ſeems plain to me, that St. <hi>Clement</hi> gives this Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, not to the Rightful Presbyters, but to thoſe who had ſtirred up and fomented the Differences: For not long before he exhorts <note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, c. 51.</note> all who had been the principal Authors and Abettors of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and Diſſention, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the common Good more than their own private Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; for thoſe who lived in Charity, would rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn themſelves, than deſtroy the Order and Diſcipline of the Church; and it was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for Men to confeſs their Sins, than to harden their Hearts, as <hi>Corah</hi> and his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates did, who raiſed a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition againſt <hi>Moſes;</hi> and as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> had likewiſe done: Then he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts them to the Confeſſion of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 52.</note> their Sins from ſeveral Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges out of the Pſalms, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſets before them the Example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who in a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 53.</note> wonderful Extaſie of Zeal and Charity for the People, who had ſacrificed to the molten Calf, deſired rather to be him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf blotted out of God's Book, than that they ſhould periſh; and then ſays, that if there were any among them of a generous and charitable and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 54.</note> truly Chriſtian Spirit, he would depart; and go whither they pleaſed, if ſo be, the People would live quietly and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably under the Presbyters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted over them. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <note place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 55.</note> the Example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he proceeds to take notice, that among the Gentiles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Kings and other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates had often expoſed their own Perſons to danger and ruin for the Preſervation of their People, and others had left their Countrey rather than they would be the occaſion of any diſturbance in it; nay, that many Chriſtians had to his own knowledg delivered themſelves up into Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to redeem others, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny had ſold themſelves for Slaves to feed others with the Price of their own Servitude: And among the Jews, <hi>Judith</hi> and <hi>Eſther</hi> refuſed no Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers for the Deliverance of their Nation. <note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. c. 56.</note> 
               <hi>Let us then,</hi> ſays he, <hi>pray for thoſe who are in fault,</hi> 
               <note n="(*)" place="bottom">So it muſt be tranſlated, if we read <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as it is in the Text, and not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as it is, by conjecture only, put in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</note> 
               <hi>that</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57618:20"/> 
               <hi>Meekneſs and Humility may be given them, that they may yield, not to us, but to the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll of God.</hi> And becauſe this might ſeem a hard ſaying to many, and too difficult to be put in practice, he ſhews them that they ought patiently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Admonition, and to ſubmit to that Correction and Chaſtiſement, which God ſhould be pleaſed to inflict either by his own Hand upon them, or by the Diſcipline of the Church: <hi>You therefore that have laid the Foundations of Sedition, ſubmit your ſelves to the Presbyters, in order to your Repentance, and be humble,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 57.</note> 
               <hi>and learn to be obedient; laying aſide the proud and boaſting Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogance of your Tongue; for it is better to be one of the little ones, who are approved of in the Flock of Chriſt, than by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring too high, to fall ſhort of your hope;</hi> or, <note n="*" place="margin">16 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. marg.</note> 
               <hi>to be caſt out of the Fold.</hi> The Force of St<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Clement</hi>'s Diſcourſe ſeems to be this, that if <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſo indulgent and affectionate towards the People who had ſinned ſo heinouſly againſt God; this ought to be a powerful Motive to thoſe, who had been themſelves cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, to reſign up all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Intereſts for the Peace of the Church; and if it had been ſo uſual for the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and worthy Perſons to ſacrifice their own Safety and Honours to the publick, it might much rather be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from ſuch as had them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves given the firſt occaſion to the Diviſions in the Church. His Deſign is the ſame that <hi>Dionyſius</hi> afterwards had in his Letter to <hi>Novation,</hi> and that he might perſuade them the more effectually to deſiſt from their Pretenſions, he tells them that this was no more than the moſt worthy and heroick Perſons had done before them; not upbraiding them too ſeverely with their paſt Miſcarriages, and preſing it upon them as a Duty, which in juſtice they were bound to, and which was the leaſt ſatisfaction they could make to the Church, to forbear thoſe Practices which had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo much Diſturbance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but proceeding in a more gentle Method; and yet in the mean time not failing to let them know, that he required them not to reſign any Right, but to deſiſt from an unjuſt Claim, which was the leaſt that could be expected of them; but if it ſhould ſeem grievous to Men who had been ſo long puffed up with vain Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations, and high Conceits of themſelves, to be thus hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at laſt, he acquaints them, that they muſt conſider, that the Chaſtiſements of God muſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57618:20"/> be born with patience in much ſeverer inſtances than this affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which they had brought upon themſelves, and that however irkſom it might now ſeem, it would bring Peace and Joy to them in the end.</p>
            <p>But if we underſtand St. <hi>Clement,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Hody</hi> does, to exhort thoſe, who were the lawful Presbyters to reſign their Right, rather than be the occaſion, through the Wickedneſs and Injuſtice of others towards them, of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Diſorder to the Church, we muſt neceſſarily ſuppoſe ſome extraordinary Circumſtances, which made St. <hi>Clement</hi> adviſe them to this Condeſcenſion in their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Caſe. For it is not to be imagined that he ſhould lay it down as a general Rule in all Caſes, that a Biſhop or Presbyter, whenever he is moleſted or diſpoſſeſſed, muſt give way to the Intruder for Peace ſake; but we muſt of neceſſity underſtand this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and Admonition in ſome ſuch qualified ſenſe, as we do thoſe Commands of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelf, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 39, 40.</note> 
               <hi>ſmite thee on the right cheek, turn to him the other alſo. And if any man will ſue thee at the law, and take away thy coat, let him have thy cloak alſo.</hi> For to oblige all honeſt Men to ſuffer themſelves to be abuſed, and to give up their Rights of any kind for the ſake of Peace and Quietneſs, would be ſo far from being a means to procure Peace, that it would be the readieſt and moſt effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual way to all manner of Confuſion in the World. So that the utmoſt that this Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation from St. <hi>Clement</hi> can amount to, is only thus much, that for ſome ſpecial Reaſons, and in ſome extraordinary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, it would be an act of great Charity and worthy of a Chriſtian, for a Biſhop to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend ſo far, as to recede from his own Right; which affords nothing in proof of that Doctrin, that this Greek Author is publiſhed to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, <hi>That although a Biſhop was unjuſtly deprived, neither he nor the Church ever made a Separation; if the Succeſſor was not an Heretick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Quotations from St. <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus,</hi> and from the Apoſtles Conſtitutions are excellent Cautions and Perſuaſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Schiſms in general, but do not in the leaſt concern the Cauſe before us. And I heartily pray, that either their Authority or any other may have the effect, which it ought, upon thoſe, who are moſt concerned ſeriouſly to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of them, towards the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57618:21"/> a Schiſm, which ſeems to threaten the Deſtruction of the beſt Church in the World; to the Ruin whereof nothing can more contribute, than to teach that <hi>a Biſhop, when once depoſed, tho never ſo</hi> 
               <note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Ego actus ab epiſcopatu, quantumvis per injuriam ſummam.</hi> ceſſo eſſe veſter Epiſcopus, &amp;c. <hi>Mr.</hi> Hody<hi>'s Preface.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>unjuſtly, ceaſes to be any longer Biſhop of his See:</hi> Which are Words now put into St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Mouth; but how much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all reaſon and probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity has been already ſhewn.</p>
            <p>In the Book it ſelf, where it is ſaid, that <hi>Meletius</hi> was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 1.</note> tranſlated from <hi>Sebaſtia</hi> to <hi>Antioch,</hi> Euſtathius <hi>being yet in Baniſhment;</hi> in the Engliſh Edition this <hi>Euſtathius</hi> is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be Euſtathius <hi>late Biſhop of</hi> Sebaſtia: But in the Greek and Latin Edition, <hi>Euſtathius late Biſhop of</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 4.</note> and a Note is ſubjoyn'd to inform us, that both <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> and <hi>Sozomen</hi> ſay, that <hi>Euſtathius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> lived till the Reign o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Valens,</hi> and that the Arguments which <hi>Baronius</hi> and <hi>Valeſius</hi> bring to the contrary, are not of weight enough to be ſet againſt the Authority of theſe two Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baronius</hi> argues, that <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtathius</hi> of <hi>Antioch</hi> never lived to be recalled from Baniſhment by <hi>Jovian,</hi> but died in exile under <hi>Conſtantius:</hi> For if he had been recalled, it cannot be ſuppoſed, that no mention ſhould be made of him in the Synod of <hi>Antioch,</hi> which was held at that time by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox; and beſides neither <hi>Meletius</hi> nor <hi>Paulinus</hi> would have been ſuffered by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Antioch</hi> to be confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, and reſide there as their Biſhop, if he had been ſtill living, without their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding into Parties about it; ſince a great part of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox from their great Zeal and Affection for him were denominated <hi>Euſtathians.</hi> And if <hi>Euſtathius</hi> had ſurvived his Baniſhment, there is no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but both <hi>Meletius</hi> and <hi>Paulinus</hi> would have reſigned the See to him at his return. For <hi>Meletius</hi> was put into that See at the earneſt deſire of the orthodox Biſhops after the Baniſhment of <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> and he who was ſo condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending to <hi>Paulinus,</hi> would have yielded much more to <hi>Euſtathius</hi> himſelf: For all the pretence that <hi>Paulinus</hi> could have, was to be Biſhop over a Party of Men, who for the great Veneration they had for <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> were called <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians;</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57618:21"/> and who would not live in communion with <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letius,</hi> becauſe he had been ordained by <hi>Arians:</hi> And it is abſurd to think that <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus,</hi> the chief of the <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi> Party, would retain his Biſhoprick, if <hi>Euſtathius</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had been yet living; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs perhaps we ſay, that <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtathius</hi> had wholly relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed his See to him, and that he lived concealed at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> or in ſome other place from the time of his firſt Baniſhment (as <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Sozomen</hi> ſay, he did, in the Reign of <hi>Valens)</hi> till he was a ſecond time baniſhed. But to put this out of all Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, <hi>Theodorite</hi> expreſly <note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theod. lib. 3. cap. 4.</note> ſays, that <hi>Euſtathius</hi> was dead before <hi>Meletius</hi> ſucceeded him in the See of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and his Authority alone, without any concurring Evidence, is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to oppoſe to that of <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Sozomen:</hi> But if it were not, beſides what has been already ſaid, their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, as <hi>Valeſius</hi> obſerves, diſagrees from what St. <hi>Hierom</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Valeſ. ad Socr. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 15.</note> and <hi>Theodorus Lector,</hi> and <hi>Theophanes</hi> relate concerning this <hi>Euſtathius:</hi> So that we muſt conclude, that <hi>Euſtathius</hi> of <hi>Sebaſtia</hi> is meant by the Greek Author, or elſe that this is another of his Miſtakes.</p>
            <p>In the Greek it is ſaid, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note> that <hi>Arſacius becauſe of the Jealouſie of his Brother</hi> Necta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius <hi>towards him, had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſworn, that he would never accept of the See of</hi> Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople. But in the Engliſh this is omitted in the Text, and ſet down only in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, with this Note; that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>the Manuſcript in this place is written erroneouſly.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hody</hi> in the Greek and Latin Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion takes no notice, that this is an Error, being more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der now, it ſeems, of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of his Author, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of <hi>Palladius</hi> too, from <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pallad. p.</hi> 94.</note> whom he had it.</p>
            <p>I wiſh Mr. <hi>Hody</hi> had been as careful of his Author's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and of his own too in all other Reſpects as in this. And after ſuch Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations of ſincere and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Intentions in publiſhing this Manuſcript, it could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be imagined that he had omitted any thing, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to this wonderful Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, which he ſo much values and ſo highly magnifies: But it is an unlucky thing to be engaged in a Cauſe, which no Author ever yet had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of the <hi>Greek</hi> in him
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57618:22"/> to maintain; and therefore, as I am well aſſured, <hi>he has left out a Collection of Canons at the end of the Manuſcript written in the ſame hand, and by the ſame Author; which ſhews that the Author is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of ſynodical Deprivations:</hi> For, ſince there were no ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodical Proce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dings in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Deprivations, that part of the Manuſcript muſt be ſuppreſſed, leſt it ſhould make all the reſt impertinent to the Controverſie ariſing from the preſent ſtate of our Church, tho it were all as true, as I have ſhewn it to be falſe. The Canons annexed are a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Anſwer to the Book, as far as we are concerned in it, and therefore it was great Prudence to conceal them. This looks as if <hi>Malela</hi> were not only fabulous, but infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious too, and will be apt to make Men ſuſpect, that <hi>Malela</hi> himſelf is worſe in the Print than in the Manuſcript.</p>
            <p>And this is all that I ſhall ſay, and I think a great deal more than was neceſſary to be ſaid, of a Book, which inſtead of being ſent into the World with ſo much Oſtentation and Triumph, would have been in danger of a publick Cenſure at any other time but this, ſince the Reformation; except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only that Interval, when we had all our Biſhops depoſed at once. And to endeavour to maintain a Cauſe by ſuch Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and ſuch Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>horities, as are both notoriouſly falſe, and of ſo pernicious conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that they would have been ſuffered at no other time, and any other Cauſe would have been aſhamed of them; and then to be forced too up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch Arts, as may be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary in an ill Cauſe, but would never ſurely be uſed in a good one, is no leſs than a Confeſſion of the badneſs of a Cauſe; and is ſo far from being a Defence, that it is an evident ſign, that it cannot be defended.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="canons">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:57618:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> CANONS <hi>in the</hi> Baroccian <hi>Manuſcripts omitted by Mr.</hi> Hody.</head>
            <div type="canon">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The</hi> XXXI. <hi>Canon of the Holy</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>by a Miſtake for the</hi> XXXII.</head>
               <p>IF any Presbyter, contemning <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can. Ap.</hi> 32.</note> his own Biſhop, ſhall hold a ſeparate Meeting, and erect an oppoſite Altar, having nothing wherewith to charge the Biſhop in Matters of <note n="‡" place="margin">or <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </note> Piety and Juſtice, let him be depoſed, as an ambitious Affector of Government; for he is an Uſurper. In like manner, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Clergy that ſhall joyn with him, ſhall be depoſed, and the Laicks excommunicated: But all this ought to be done after the firſt, the ſecond, and third Admonition of the Biſhop.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="canon">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The</hi> VI. <hi>Canon of the Synod of</hi> Gangra.</head>
               <p>If any Man hold a private Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Synod. Gangr.</hi> Can. 6.</note> out of the Church, and deſpiſing the Church, ſhall preſume to perform the Offices of the Church <note n="†" place="margin">Note that in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, inſtead of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> as the printed Canons have it.</note>, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiating Presbyter not being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto licenſed by the Biſhop, let him be Anathema.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="canon">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The</hi> V. <hi>Canon of the Synod of</hi> Antioch.</head>
               <p>If any Presbyter or Deacon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Syn. Antioch.</hi> Can. 5.</note> his own Biſhop hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelf from the Church, and ſet up an Altar in a private Meeting, and ſhall diſobey the Admonitions of the Biſhop, and will not be perſwaded by him, nor ſubmit to him, exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him again and again, he is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to be depoſed; and ought no longer to be treated as a curable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, neither as one who can retain his Honour; and if he ſhall perſevere to make Tumults and Diſturbances in the Church, he is to be turned over, as a ſeditious Perſon to the ſecular Power.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="canon">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The</hi> XV. <hi>Canon of the ſame Synod.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If any Biſhop accus'd of any Crimes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eiuſd. Synodi</hi> Can. 15.</note> be condemned by all the <hi>Biſhops of the Province,</hi> who have all with one accord denounced the ſame Sentence againſt him, ſuch a one by no means ought to be judged again by others; but the concordant Sentence of the Provincial Biſhops ought to remain firm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="canon">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The</hi> X. <hi>Canon of the Synod of</hi> Carthage.</head>
               <p>If any Presbyter being puffed up <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Syn. Carth.</hi> Can. 10.</note> againſt his own Biſhop, ſhall make a Schiſm, let him be Anathema.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="canon">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:57618:23"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The</hi> XIII. <hi>Can. of the Syn. of</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>called the 1ſt. and</hi> 2<hi>d. Synod.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Devil having ſown the Seeds <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> of Heretical Tares in the Church of Chriſt, and ſeeing them cut up by the roots by the Sword of the Spirit, hath betaken himſelf to a new way and method. <hi>viz</hi> to divide the Church by the madneſs of Shiſmaticks: But the holy Synod being alſo willing to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate this Stratagem of his, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed as followeth; If any Presbyter or Deacon, under the pretence of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing his own Biſhop of any Crimes, ſhall preſume to withdraw from his Communion, and not mention his Name in the holy Prayers of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy according to the Tradition of the Church <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>, <hi>before Synodical Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Tryal,</hi> ſuch a one ſhall be depoſed and deprived of all ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Honour; for he that is in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a Prieſt, and ſhall uſurp the Power of Judging belonging to the Metropolitans, and as much as in him lies ſhall condemn his own Father and Biſhop, before Sentence pronounced by them, he is worthy neither of the Honour nor Appellation of a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and thoſe who are Followers of ſuch a one, if they are in holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, even any of them ſhall be degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from his proper Honour; but if they are Monks, or Laicks, they ſhall by all means be excommunicated from the Church, until abhorring the Converſation of Schiſmaticks they ſhall return unto their proper Biſhop.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="canon">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The</hi> XIV. <hi>Canon of the ſame Synod.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If any Biſhop, pretending an Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Synodi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 14.</note> againſt his Metropolitan <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Synodical Judgment,</hi> ſhall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelf from communion with him, and ſhall not recite his Name ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to cuſtom in Divine Service, the holy Synod hath decreed that ſuch a one ſhall be depoſed, if after private <note n="‡" place="margin">or <hi>Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  </note> Admonition he ſhall depart from his own Metropolitan, and make a Schiſm: For it behoves every one to know his own proper bounds, and that neither the Presbyter deſpiſe his own proper Biſhop, nor the Biſhop his own Metropolitan.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="canon">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The</hi> XV. <hi>Canon of the ſame Synod.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Theſe Decrees concerning Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Synodi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Biſhops and Metropolitans, agree alſo to <hi>Patriarchs;</hi> So that if any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or Metropolitan ſhall preſume to depart from Communion with his own Patriarch, and ſhall not mention his Name in the Divine Offices, as is decreed and ordered, but ſhall make <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> a Separation * before Synodical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, and final Condemnation of him; the holy Synod hath decreed, that ſuch a one be abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed from all ſacred Orders, if he offend in this kind after private <note n="‡" place="margin">or <hi>Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  </note> Admonition. And theſe things are decreed and enacted concerning thoſe who under pretence of any Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions revolt from their own Superiors, and make a Schiſm, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, In the print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Canon.</note> 
                  <hi>and break the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church.</hi> But if any ſhall ſeparate themſelves from Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with their Superior for any He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie condemned by the holy Synods and Fathers, he publickly preaching the ſame Hereſie to the People, and teaching it bare-faced in the Church, ſuch ſhall not only be free from Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Cenſure for ſeparating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from Communion with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſo called <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>before Synodical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,</hi> but they ſhall be thought worthy of the Honour that is due to the Orthodox, becauſe they have not condemned a Biſhop, but a falſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and a falſe Teacher, and have not divided the Unity of the Church by Schiſm, but have ſtudiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to preſerve the Church from Schiſms and Diviſions.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57618:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
